<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apologie for our publick ministerie and infant-baptism written som years ago for private satisfaction of som dissenting brethren and upon request enlarged and published for the same ends / by William Lyford.</title>
            <author>Lyford, William, 1598-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24102</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07951777</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07951777</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1210:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apologie for our publick ministerie and infant-baptism written som years ago for private satisfaction of som dissenting brethren and upon request enlarged and published for the same ends / by William Lyford.</title>
                  <author>Lyford, William, 1598-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Du Gard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apologetics --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40677:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGIE For our Publick Miniſterie, AND Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Written ſom years ago for Private ſatisfaction of ſom Diſſenting Brethren; and upon requeſt enlarged and Publiſhed for the ſame ends.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Lyford,</hi> B.D. and Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Sherborn</hi> in <hi>Dorcetſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEUT. 12.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Take heed to thy ſelf, that thou forſake not the Levite, as long as thou liveſt upon the earth.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 THES. 5.12, 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wee beſeech you brethren to know them, which labor among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you, and esteem them very highly in love for their works ſake, and bee at peace among your ſelves.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lux. 10.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hee that heareth you heareth mee; and hee that deſpiſeth you deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth mee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Dugard,</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40677:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40677:2"/>
            <head>To my loving Chriſtian friend, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Raymond</hi> wiſheth increaſ of Grace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to your earneſt deſire and my promiſs, I have ſent up unto you the <hi>heads</hi> of thoſe Reaſons with large additions, which four years ago I tendred to ſom of our <hi>Church-forſakers,</hi> with hope to have gained them to unitie and communion with us. But by that time <hi>Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching</hi> was counted a fine knack, and our Engliſh people taught to queſtion the Calling of their Miniſters, to <hi>call them</hi> by new names, <hi>Baals Prieſts,</hi> the <hi>black guard, Antichriſtian Prieſts, &amp;c.</hi> And then 'tis high time to ſet up themſelvs; if they had lived in the primitive times, when Chriſtians did meet in dens and ſecret places for the worſhip of Christ, with hazard of their lives, they would have counted it a <hi>bleſſed privilege</hi> to enjoy the free uſe of the Ordinances in <hi>publike Aſſemblies;</hi> but now that libertie is granted, it is deſpiſed; our people are wanton and unthankful. Surely our Lord Chriſt was no <hi>Corner-creeping Preacher,</hi> Hee diſclaimed it, I ſpake openly to the world, I ever taught in the <hi>Synagogue, whither the Jews reſort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 18.20.</note> and in <hi>ſecret</hi> have I ſaid nothing: Neither doth hee <hi>allow it</hi> in his ſervants, whom hee forwarns not to ſeek him in <hi>Corners, Mat. 24.26</hi> if they ſhall ſay unto you, Behold he is in the deſart [among thoſe which withdraw themſelvs from the publike profeſſors,] <hi>Go not forth;</hi> Behold hee is in the <hi>ſecret Chambers, Believ it not.</hi> When men ſhall ſay unto you, in ſuch a houſ or Chamber, there is one that hold's forth Chriſt moſt ſweetly in a Goſpel-way, let us go to him; Go not forth, ſaies the Text, <hi>Believ it not:</hi> How ſhould any <hi>believ it?</hi> for what <hi>one new ſweet Doctrine</hi> concerning Christ his perſon, or offices <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave yee learned there, which yee were not taught before. Have yee <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y your new way</hi> gotten farther aſſurance of your ſalvation?
<pb facs="tcp:40677:3"/>Have yee thereby grown <hi>in grace, and more eſcaped</hi> the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are in the world through lust? or are yee more <hi>intangled</hi> in the ſame? <hi>What?</hi> Chriſt ſweetly held forth, and yet no <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> of that knowledg ſtick upon your ſouls? I demand with S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.4.</note> Hee that cometh and preacheth, doth hee preach <hi>another Jeſus,</hi> whom wee have not preached, or <hi>another</hi> ſpirit, or <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goſpel</hi> which yee have not accepted? <hi>Chriſt held forth in private,</hi> is it the <hi>ſame Chriſt,</hi> or another? the ſame way of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, the ſame ſpirit of ſanctification, which wee have taught, <hi>or another?</hi> if <hi>another,</hi> I boldly affirm it, it is a falſ Chriſt, a falſ Goſpel, a falſ ſpirit: But <hi>if the ſame,</hi> why do people deſert the Ordinance, as if it were not the ſame? Yes, becauſ other men have a better way of Teaching Chriſt, and wee go not from <hi>one Chriſt to another,</hi> but to the ſame Chriſt held forth in a ſweeter manner. <hi>Anſw.</hi> If that bee the <hi>intent,</hi> then it is your <hi>wiſeſt and ſureſt</hi> way to partake of both, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſing of God</hi> in the Aſſemblies, and of the <hi>help of anothers gifts,</hi> either before or after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, by which means you will avoid the <hi>ſcandal now given</hi> (which an honeſt man will make conſcience to do,) and you'l bee <hi>ſure to meet</hi> with Christ, if hee bee any where manifeſted.</p>
            <p>SIR, You may remember that I have often <hi>invited the people</hi> to com to mee, and open their doubts, which ſom have don (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when <hi>ſelf-examination</hi> of our ſpiritual eſtates was more in uſe amongſt Christians.) Yea, I have <hi>offered,</hi> that if any ſoul <hi>could think</hi> of any matter or Text which might ſerv to anſwer their doubts, to <hi>eaſ their ſcruples,</hi> to <hi>direct their Conſciences</hi> in particular Caſes, or to <hi>inform their mindes</hi> in any point or Text not uſually handled, that they ſhould <hi>chuſe the way</hi> to acquaint mee with their deſires, and I would ſtudie to anſwer their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I do not remember, that any made uſe of this <hi>liberty,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides your ſelf, who once deſired mee to preach upon that Text, <hi>Joh. 6.44.</hi> which I readily did in two Sermons, and ſhall <hi>as readily</hi> do the like, for <hi>any ſoul</hi> in the Congregation. I have not uſed
<pb facs="tcp:40677:3"/>to trouble their heads with Controverſies of the times; but when I had <hi>finiſhed my Bodie</hi> of Divinitie, (which was the <hi>ſubject of my morning Sermons,</hi> wherein I aimed chiefly at Laying of foundations, as in the afternoons Sermons, going through ſom entire piece of Scripture (as the whole Epistle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi>) wherein I aimed eſpecially at <hi>larger Applications for inſtruction in holineſs and trials</hi> of our ſpiritual eſtate.) In the year <hi>1647.</hi> The <hi>Teſtimonie of the London Miniſters</hi> againſt the Errors of the times coming forth, I (to avoid ſuſpicion of loading the times with Errors,) did take the <hi>Opinions</hi> as they were there drawn up to my hands and upon <hi>each head,</hi> I laid down <hi>one or two diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> very breifly (not by <hi>Obj.</hi> and <hi>Sol.</hi>) that ſo by <hi>ſorting every</hi> thing apart, the Chaff by it ſelf, the Wheat by it ſelf;<note place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note> my people might have their <hi>ſenſes</hi> exerciſed <hi>to diſcern</hi> both good and evil, and ſee in <hi>which ſide</hi> of the <hi>diſtinction lay the Truth</hi> and in which the Error,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.10.</note> and ſo neither <hi>condemn all</hi> nor <hi>imbrace all things</hi> in the Lump, but bee able to diſcern things that differ. In all which, as in the <hi>courſ</hi> of my miniſterie, with all caution and tenderneſs avoiding this, <hi>Never to encourage any thing of the fleſh, nor diſcourage any thing of the ſpirit in my Hearers.</hi> The which exerciſes, if God bee pleaſed to reſtore my health, I intend ſhortly to reviſe and publiſh.</p>
            <p>Learned men will wonder, why I ſhould come forth <hi>now in the Fag end</hi> of the day with a <hi>ſtale</hi> Controverſie: But ſo long as ſin reign's, we ought not to bee ſilent. Varietie of Books, though for <hi>matter the ſame,</hi> is of good uſe: You ſee that notwithstanding all the <hi>Ammunition</hi> in the<note n="*" place="margin">Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth or Nation.</note> 
               <hi>Kingdom,</hi> there is <hi>new made daily,</hi> ſome are naked, or the old is lost; ſo it is in Books, which are more needful then Arms, all com not into all hands, many would <hi>read little,</hi> if Books were <hi>not new.</hi> It's noted of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> that they got the ſway of the world, and overtopt the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> partly by their <hi>ſubtilty crerping</hi> into Emperors Courts, partly by their unwearied diligence; the Orthodox after <hi>ſound Confutation</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:40677:4"/>their Hereſie, ſitting down <hi>content with that diſcharge</hi> of their dutie: And ſurely if ever our glorious lights of the ſanctuarie bee put out, and <hi>new ones</hi> ſet up in their ſtead, next unto God's wrath <hi>penally inflicting</hi> ſuch a judgment for a Peoples unthankfulneſs, it will bee aſcribed to our <hi>lazineſs, and their unwearied dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> rather then to any truth of their Cauſ; or excellence of their Arguing: For they do not or will not know <hi>when they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed,</hi> but after their Arguments anſwered ten times over, they are as <hi>brisk to offer new.</hi> diſputation, inſiſting upon their old bald Arguments, as if <hi>never uttered before;</hi> their diligence ſhould provoke us to the like, if not their diligence, yet love to their ſouls <hi>ſhould,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.</note> remembring that of <hi>Paul,</hi> in meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelvs, if at any time God will give them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to the <hi>acknowledging</hi> of the truth, that they may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover</hi> themſelvs out of the ſnare of the Divel, wee muſt not give <hi>over a Patient</hi> while there is hope, no not though they <hi>oppoſe themſelvs,</hi> but with long-ſuffering they muſt bee instructed, becauſ as the <hi>gift of grace,</hi> ſo the <hi>time of grace</hi> is in God's hand alone. It is a great <hi>skill to diſcern</hi> who are to bee forborn and who to bee oppoſed, they that make <hi>Diviſions and parties</hi> in the Church and ſcandalize the Doctrine are to bee avoided,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> others that walk <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and peaceably</hi> under that <hi>weakneſs and diſſenting Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> from their brethren, are to bee forborn, loved, and cheriſhed, till wee meet in heaven, where <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>all,</hi> whoſe <hi>Faith and hearts do center</hi> in the Lord Chriſt, ſhall for evermore bee fully agreed. To his Grace I commend you, who is able to eſtabliſh you, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, and the Churches ſervant in the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, WILLIAM LYFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40677:4"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGIE FOR Our Publick MINISTERIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ouching the Office and Calling of Miniſters, and Lay-men's preaching, the Queſtion is not, Whether Chriſtians may and ought privately to edifie one another by admonitions, counſels, reproofs, repetition of Sermons, reading of good Books and other Chriſtian conferences, all this I grant and commend to practice from theſe Scriptures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15 14. But the whole ſtate of the controverſie may fitly bee reduced to theſe three heads:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Whether the work of a Miniſter in the Adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments, bee a Calling, Office and work <hi>diſtinct</hi> from the reſt of the people? Whether there bee any ſuch Calling or Office for that holy work in the New Teſtament? Affir.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether Ordination of Miniſters for Adminiſtration of Word and Sacraments bee an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Chriſt in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament? Affir.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether it bee lawful for men <hi>uncalled</hi> and <hi>unordained</hi> to Take upon them the preaching of the Word in the <hi>Name</hi> and with the autoritie of the Lord Jeſus, or the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments? Neg.</p>
            <p>The anſwer and determination of theſe three Queſtions will clearly ſtate the Cauſ, which I ſhall do in three Concluſions.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40677:5"/>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>1</label> 1. The Miniſterie is a <hi>diſtinct Calling</hi> and <hi>Office,</hi> which they are bound to attend unto, and None but they can or ought to perform.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>2</label> 2. <hi>Ordination</hi> of Miniſters by impoſition of hands of other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for the Adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments, is an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of Chriſt in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label> 3. No man <hi>uncalled</hi> and <hi>unordained</hi> can with good Conſcience <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude</hi> or enter upon that Work and Office, it is a great ſin ſo to do. Of theſe I will ſpeak in order.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt Concluſion in Anſwer to the firſt Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Miniſterie</hi> is a diſtinct Office and Calling, is proved 1. By expreſs words of the Text, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. if any man deſire the <hi>Office of a Biſhop,</hi> hee deſireth a good work: The Text tell's you that <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter,</hi> is an <hi>Office,</hi> a <hi>good Office,</hi> and hee that is made a Biſhop is a man in high Office, even to take care of the Church of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. and in him there are required manie qualifications which are not required in other Believers. Again, <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Philippians</hi> doth plainly diſtinguiſh the <hi>Bodie</hi> of Saints from the <hi>Officers, To all the Saints which are at</hi> Philippi <hi>with the Biſhops and Deacons,</hi> Phil. 1.1. By Biſhops there, all underſtand Miniſters of the Goſpel, in Office of Teaching diſtinct from the people, <hi>who were Saints, but not Biſhops.</hi> So in the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the like <hi>diſtinction</hi> between Paſtor and People in reſpect of Office and Calling is obferved. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. <hi>Paul</hi> called for the <hi>Elders</hi> of the Church, <hi>verſ</hi> 17. Hee minde's them of their <hi>Office, verſ</hi> 28. Take heed to all the flock over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you <hi>overſeers or Biſhops,</hi> to feed the Church of God, for ſo did Chriſt ordain, and ſet in the Church ſom Paſtors and Teachers for the <hi>work of the Ministerie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eheſ. 4.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>e.i.</hi> to bee Guides to the Flock, to feed them with wholſom Doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17. Remember them which have the <hi>Rule over</hi> you, who have <hi>ſpoken unto you</hi> the Word of God, and ſubmit your ſelvs, for they watch for your ſouls. In which places you ſee that <hi>Miniſterie of the Word</hi> is a name of <hi>Office</hi> given to <hi>certain men deſigned and ſingled</hi> out to that work, as a ſpecial work not <hi>common</hi> to others, take one clear place more, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11. Comfort and edifie one another, [there's the <hi>peoples mutual dutie</hi> in private.] But <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. know them which <hi>labor among</hi> you and are <hi>over you in the Lord</hi> and admoniſh you, there's the <hi>Paſtor's Office</hi> and dutie, who, though they may bee but <hi>even with you</hi> in reſpect of Gifts and Graces, yet they are <hi>over you in the Lord:</hi> in reſpect of their Office and Work, they are over all, even <hi>over them which were able
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40677:5"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>1</label> privately</hi> to admoniſh one another; and the people's dutie is to <hi>know, i.e.</hi> to acknowledg them as ſuch, and to eſteem them very highly for their work's ſake, becauſ God hath ſet them over you in that Office.</p>
            <p>By all which places of Scripture it is evident that in the <hi>Churches</hi> of Chriſt
<list>
                  <item>Som are Paſtors and Elders to feed Some are Guides and Rulers</item>
                  <item>Som are Sheep &amp; the flock to bee fed Som are Guided and Ruled.</item>
                  <item>Som are ſingle Saints:</item>
                  <item>Som are Biſhops over them in the Lord.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>There is a <hi>work wholly</hi> to bee attended, and men <hi>appointed to attend</hi> that work <hi>wholly. Names</hi> of <hi>Office,</hi> without an Office, are meer mockeries; the Names of a King, of a Steward, Paſtor, Biſhop, Guide, &amp;c. without their reſpective Offices are not given in Scripture; In the places now cited, you finde thoſe <hi>diſtinctive</hi> Titles and Names joyned with the work it ſelf. I demand then with the Apoſtle, Are all <hi>Teachers?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.28. Rom. 14.4.</note> are all <hi>Biſhops?</hi> are all Guids and Paſtors? The Miniſter and his Work are as <hi>preciſely</hi> diſtinguiſhed by the holy Ghoſt from <hi>all other Callings,</hi> as can bee written with ink and paper. Now that which Chriſt hath ſet up, who ſhall dare to pull down? Thoſe which Chriſt hath diſtinguiſhed, no may <hi>confound.</hi> Paſtor and People, Biſhops and Flock, Guides and guided are <hi>relatives,</hi> and ſtand in ſuch direct <hi>oppoſition</hi> one to the other, that, in reſpect of the ſame ſubject, the <hi>one</hi> cannot bee the <hi>other:</hi> the Father is not the Son, nor the Son the Father; the Maſter is not the Servant, nor the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant the Maſter; the King is not a ſubject, nor a ſubject the King; And therefore <hi>regularly,</hi> the one cannot do the duties of the other. A Guifted man, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> is not a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> nor a Presbyter, nor a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, for theſe are diſtinguiſhed from other men, that have <hi>Gifts,</hi> but <hi>not Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, This firſt Concluſion is proved from the ſpecial <hi>Charge</hi> given to Miniſters, over and above what is incumbent on private perſons, as for example, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. Take heed to the Miniſterie which thou haſt received of the Lord that thou fulfil it—and to all the Flock over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you over-ſeers, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. with 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. Take heed to thy ſelf and to the Doctrine, meditate upon theſe things, Give thy ſelf wholly to them, <hi>i.e.</hi> to Reading, Exhortation and Doctrine, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.15. The work to which thou waſt ordained, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. And as God hath given a <hi>Charge</hi> to Miniſters, ſo hee doth require an exact <hi>account</hi> of their doings in this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40677:6"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>1</label> kinde. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 3. I charge thee before God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.18. Ezek. 34.2, 4, 10. Zech. 11.17.</note> who ſhall judg the quick and the dead at his appearing, preach the Word, bee inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long-ſuffering and Doctrine: This is the <hi>Miniſters Charge.</hi> Now <hi>all</hi> do not lie under this weightie Charge and account. Hath every <hi>Gifted</hi> man a Flock to feed? a <hi>Miniſterie</hi> to fulfil? or are they <hi>bound to give themſelvs wholly</hi> to that work forſaking all other Callings? No, but they are perſons <hi>ſingled out</hi> and deſigned to this Office and Work, upon whom this Charge doth lie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our third proof is from the honor and maintenance appointed for them that preach the Goſpel, the Lord hath <hi>ordained</hi> that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14. And that the Presbyters which labor in the Word and Doctrine ſhould bee counted worthie double honor, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. And can Lay-preachers challenge this honor and maintenance?</p>
            <p>The ſum of all is this, Miniſters, and <hi>none</hi> but <hi>Miniſters,</hi> are Biſhops, Paſtors or Elders; <hi>They,</hi> and <hi>none</hi> but they, are <hi>bound</hi> to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs <hi>wholly</hi> to that work; <hi>They,</hi> and <hi>none</hi> but they, are under that heavie Charge and account; <hi>They,</hi> and <hi>none</hi> but they, can by <hi>divine Autoritie of Chriſt's ordinance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.14.</note> challenge to live of the Goſpel; <hi>They,</hi> and <hi>none</hi> but they, to whom theſe <hi>Characters</hi> do belong, are the men whom God hath made Miniſters of Chriſt and Stewards of the Myſteries of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Oject. </seg>1</label> Two Objections com to bee anſwered: For ſom do ſay, Wee preach not as men in Office, but in <hi>another capacitie, as gifted men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Anſwer, See the folly of this Objection, it is as if you would ſay, there bee <hi>two ſorts</hi> of Preachers, ſom that are appointed and ſent, and ſom that are not, and yet do it: Som preach in <hi>a preaching capacitie,</hi> and <hi>ſom not in a preaching capacitie:</hi> Som are Called, ſent and Autorized by Chriſt to preach, ſom are not ſo Autorized, and yet they preach. It is a contradiction to preach in a <hi>non-preaching capacitie,</hi> becauſ to preach <hi>in the Name and by the Autoritie</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, doth imply a publike <hi>miſſion and Autorizing;</hi> If an ordinarie Souldier ſhould uſurp the office of a <hi>Colonel,</hi> or a Colonel the office of the <hi>General,</hi> or a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man the office of a <hi>Conſtable,</hi> would this bee a good anſwer to ſay, I do it not in the <hi>capacitie</hi> of a Conſtable, or Colonel, or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but in another capacitie, as a man Gifted for ſuch actions; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev ſuch an under-taker would bee ſeverely puniſhed in the capacitie of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> of a <hi>buſie-diſturber</hi> of publike Order. His being Gifted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40677:6"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>1</label> cannot excuſe his arrogancie, becauſ thoſe offices cannot bee <hi>duly</hi> performed by <hi>any other</hi> capacitie then of their Office and Patent.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> But the better to overthrow our Office, and make no Calling of it,ſom ſay, let them <hi>work as others do,</hi> for their living. Cannot they preach without <hi>ſtudie and books?</hi> it is a ſign they preach <hi>not by the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> See the honeſtie of this objection, It is all one as if a laborer ſhould work all the week in plowing or threſhing to provide you food, or to make you a ſuit of clothes againſt the Sabbath, were it <hi>juſtice</hi> to ſay to him at the weeks end, Go work for your living, when hee ha's been all the while about your work? Such another piece of Juſtice and Honeſtie it is to ſay, Let Miniſters work for their living, when as they <hi>have ſpent their time,</hi> and ſpirits, and Talents to do you ſervice, to prepare food and raiment for your ſouls. Chriſt count's preaching to bee a <hi>labor,</hi> elſ hee would not have ſaid, the <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borer</hi> is worthie of his hire; yea and hard labor too, elſ hee would not have compared Miniſters to ſouldiers, to ſhepherds, to husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to the labor of the ox that treadeth out the corn.</p>
            <p>Beſides,<note place="margin">1 Cor 9.13, 14</note> Chriſt hath <hi>ordained</hi> that miniſters ſhould <hi>live</hi> by their preaching, as by a Calling, as the Prieſts under the Law did: As they that miniſtred about holy things, did live of the things of the Temple, even ſo hath the Lord <hi>ordained,</hi> that they which <hi>preach the Goſpel</hi> ſhould live of the Goſpel. Theſe men oft Call for <hi>Goſpel Ordinances;</hi> Lo here is a <hi>Goſpel-Ordinance,</hi> and yet they cannot ſtoop to it; (for ſay they, let miniſters work—) But let ſuch men remember that <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint</hi> of <hi>Paul,</hi> who though hee did not regard monie, yet hee write's it up among his <hi>wrongs and ſuffrings,</hi> that hee was fain to <hi>labor for his living,</hi> working with his own hands, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11, 12. to this hour wee both hunger and thirſt, and <hi>labor working</hi> with our own hands. Therefore forbear to uſe this objection, unleſs yee mean to bee Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> To the ſecond part of the objection, do but obſerv how directly oppoſite it is to God's word. <hi>Paul</hi> bid's <hi>Timothie</hi> give <hi>attendance to Reading</hi> and to Doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. But you ſay, Can they not preach without ſtudie? <hi>Paul</hi> ſaie's <hi>verſ</hi> 15. Give thy ſelf <hi>wholly</hi> to theſe things, that thy profiting may bee known; A man ſo <hi>rarely gifred</hi> as <hi>Timothie</hi> was, of whom there went certain prophecies what a rare man hee would bee in the Church, educated from his infancie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40677:7"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>1</label> in the Scripture, <hi>yet hee muſt give attendance</hi> to ſtudie and reading, and that <hi>whollie,</hi> all is little enough; and muſt not wee much more fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our ſtudies?<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaie's, wee muſt not <hi>intangle</hi> our ſelvs in worldly imploiments. But you ſay, a man may follow a <hi>Trade all the week,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> and yet preach the Lord's day. True, after a <hi>wilde faſhion,</hi> but not like a workman that need not bee aſhamed, rightly dividing the word of truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> To the third part of the objection, I ſay, it is a mere deluding of people to ſet the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God againſt <hi>God's means,</hi> in and by which his Spirit doth uſually work. The Spirit is it which worketh <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually</hi> in the miniſterie of us all,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.8.</note> the <hi>ſufficiencie,</hi> and <hi>efficiencie</hi> is not of us, but of God, but yet the <hi>Spirit worketh by ſuch Gifts as himſelf beſtoweth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. There bee diverſities of Gifts, but the ſame Spirit, and by the <hi>right uſe</hi> of thoſe Gifts, the Spirit doth work to the edifying of the Churches; For the <hi>manifeſtation</hi> of the Spirit is given to every one to profit withall. <hi>i.e.</hi> Whoſoëver hath <hi>any Gift manifeſting</hi> the miraculous power of the Spirit, it is given, not for <hi>oſtentation,</hi> or to bee admired, but for this onely end, for the profit of all, <hi>verſ</hi> 7. Now the Gifts then given to profit the Church withall, in the <hi>way of instruction,</hi> are reckoned up ſix. 1. <hi>Sapientia, wiſdom,</hi> to applie Chriſtian Doctrine to Practice and Uſe of believers. 2. <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia,</hi> a knowledg of <hi>Principles</hi> and deep points of Religion. 3. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, i.e.</hi> a Gift to expound the prophecies and <hi>ſecret</hi> things of Scripture. 4. <hi>Diſcerning of ſpirits, viz fanatick</hi> and <hi>counterfeit</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations from true. 5. <hi>Divers kindes of tongues,</hi> that all Nations and languages might hear and underſtand the Goſpel. 6. <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of tongues</hi> wherewith <hi>others</hi> did ſpeak, and wherein the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is written: Theſe Gifts of the Spirit are <hi>uſeful</hi> and profitable for the Church, they were miraculous for the <hi>manner of coming by them,</hi> but the Doctrine taught was the ſame which was before reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Theſe Gifts may either bee <hi>acquired,</hi> or <hi>infuſed; At firſt</hi> they were <hi>infuſed</hi> immediately, both for the honor of the Goſpel, and the ſpeedier ſpreading of it; Afterwards they are <hi>continued</hi> for the good of the Church by the <hi>Help of ſtudie or praier:</hi> Even as the Gift of <hi>Healing</hi> is now continued by the ſtudie and Art of Phyſick; without the <hi>Gifts of wiſdom,</hi> ſcience, and tongues, wee can never ſoundly, nor fruitfully make known the myſteries of Scripture; and hee that by ſtudie and praier doe's <hi>attain the uſe of any of theſe Gifts in preaching,</hi> hee preacheth <hi>by the Spirit:</hi> if the <hi>Things which wee preach,</hi> bee the things
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40677:7"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> which the Spirit hath revealed in the written word, and <hi>the Gifts by which wee preach,</hi> bee the <hi>Gifts</hi> of the Spirit, then, whether the <hi>means by which wee com by thoſe Gifts,</hi> bee extraordinarie, as by inſpiration, or <hi>ordinarie,</hi> as by ſtudie and praier, the <hi>matter is the ſame,</hi> Wee <hi>preach by the Spirit, i.e.</hi> by the illumination and guidance of the Spirit, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us into the truth, which himſelf hath revealed. Wee pretend not, yea wee deteſt all pretenſions of <hi>new</hi> and <hi>immediate</hi> inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby the holie Ghoſt is made the Autor of diſorder and confuſion, or a cloak for ignorance, non-ſence and Hereſie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> Our ſecond Concluſion in Anſwer to the ſecond Queſtion in this, viz. <hi>Ordination</hi> of miniſters by impoſition of hands of the Presbyterie for the Adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments, is an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of Chriſt in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>The <hi>work of the miniſterie</hi> is an Office and Calling, as you have heard, and <hi>Ordination is Christ's Ordinance whereby fit and approved per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are ſet apart and Commiſſioned</hi> for the execution of that Office, <hi>in the Name and with the Autoritie of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Droved 1. by example.</note> The weight of the Controverſie lieth upon this Concluſion, which is directly proved. 1. By example, Wee finde in the New Teſtament four deſcents of men ſent and ordained. 1. Chriſt himſelf was ſent of his Father. 2. The Apoſtles were ſent and ordained by Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.14. 3. The Apoſtles ſent and ordained <hi>Timothie</hi> and others of their own time. 4. And they that lived in the Apoſtles times did in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ordain others to ſurvive, and do the Office of Miniſters when they were dead, and this ſucceſſion of Miniſters is to laſt to the end of the world.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt was ſent and had his Commiſſion from his Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21, 22, 23. My Father hath ſent mee. Chriſt himſelf was ſent and Autuorized to preach, elſ hee had not not taken that honor to himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4, 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Deſcent. Chriſt ſend's the Apoſtles, As my Father ſent mee, ſo ſent I you; <hi>there's their Commiſſion,</hi> hee committed the miniſterie to their execution, which himſelf had received, <hi>viz.</hi> a power to Preach and Baptize, to binde and looſ, <hi>Job.</hi> 20.23. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. Go yee therefore, Teach all Nations and Baptize them. The Man Chriſt could do nothing, but by <hi>Commiſsion from the Father,</hi> nor the Apoſtles, except <hi>Chriſt</hi> had given them Commiſſion: both Chriſt and his Apoſtles were ſolemnly inaugurated into their Office of Teaching.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40677:8"/>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Deſcent. The Apoſtles ordained <hi>Timothie</hi> and others of their own time, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. Stir up the Gift of God which is in thee, by the putting on of my hands, and the hands of the presbyterie, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. By <hi>Gift there,</hi> is meant that <hi>Ghoſtly power,</hi> or Office, which <hi>Timothie</hi> received <hi>at his ordination, by the laying on of the Apostles hands, in the preſence and with the conſent of the presbyterie,</hi> who joined with <hi>Paul</hi> in that action. Again, wee finde <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> ordaining Elders in every Church where they went, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23.</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Deſcent. <hi>Timothie</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> did <hi>ordain others,</hi> as theniſelvs had been ordained, and that by the Apoſtle's <hi>own appointment, Tit.</hi> 1.5. for this cauſ was <hi>Titus</hi> left in <hi>Crete,</hi> that hee ſhould ordain Elders in every Citie. So likewiſe <hi>Timothie</hi> is directed how to lay on hands, not ſuddenly, but with good adviſedneſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. As <hi>Timothie</hi> was entruſted with the word of Chriſt, ſo Hee muſt commit the ſame truſt to faithful men, able to teach others alſo, that ſo there may bee a ſucceſſion of Teachers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. Thus yee have recorded in Scripture four deſcents, 1. Chriſt. 2. His Apoſtles. 3. <hi>Timothie</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> 4. Elders at <hi>Creet</hi> and <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and other Churches where the Goſpel was planted, all ſent and ordained, the two later by ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the <hi>ordinarie way:</hi> thus the Apoſtles in their <hi>own Practice</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted men into the miniſterie, and thus they <hi>appointed for ſucceeding times;</hi> And can any think that Ordination ended with that Age? Is there not the ſame cauſ, neceſſitie, uſe, and reaſon for it in after Ages, as in the firſt times of the Church, when there were as yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie Gifts ſtirring in the Church, which are now ceaſed, and therefore the more need of a ſtanding miniſterie?</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2 From Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-Rules.</note> This Concluſion is proved by Scripture-<hi>Rules and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts</hi> given touching Ordination and the manner thereof: Unto <hi>Titus Paul</hi> give's commandment to ordain Elders, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe's certain <hi>Rules</hi> and Canons for the trial and qualification of them that are to bee ordained, <hi>verſ</hi> 7. a Biſhop muſt bee blameleſs, holding faſt the faithful word, that hee may bee able to convince the gainſaiers, <hi>verſ</hi> 9. So unto <hi>Timothie</hi> hee gave directions and rules touching Ordination, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22. Lay hands ſuddenly on no man, neither bee thou partaker of other mens ſins. <hi>i.e.</hi> Admit not any into the miniſterie without <hi>ſufficient examination,</hi> and good proof of their <hi>abilitie</hi> for learning, and <hi>godly converſation,</hi> elſ the blame will light upon <hi>thee,</hi> becauſ by the laying on of thy hands they were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40677:8"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> into that ſacred function. <hi>What need Titus</hi> bee left in <hi>Crete</hi> to ordain Elders in every Citie, if Saints of themſelvs might do all without Ordination? And to what purpoſe are thoſe <hi>Cautions and Directions</hi> about Ordination, if there were no ſuch thing to bee don? if Ordination it ſelf bee <hi>needleſs,</hi> then much more is the <hi>manner</hi> of doing it needleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Som think that the cerimonie of <hi>laying on of hands</hi> may bee omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: <hi>Anſ.</hi> Somtimes wee muſt bee <hi>tied</hi> to example in the leaſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, though not preſcribed, and yet men preſume to diſpenſ in a circumſtance <hi>expreſly preſcribed.</hi> Why ſhould wee bee wiſer then <hi>Paul?</hi> Why ſhould wee bee <hi>aſhamed</hi> of Gods expreſs will? <hi>Timothie</hi> was ordained by laying on of hands, and enjoined to lay on hands on others in their Ordination: thus were the Deacons ordained, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.6. and thus were <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſet apart for the execution of their Calling, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.3. And ſeeing the Scripture is ſo punctual about the <hi>Manner of Ordination,</hi> and the <hi>Qualitie of Perſons</hi> to bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, the Dutie it ſelf is much more eſtabliſhed, even as when God give's us rules for praying, faſting, alms, Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">Matth. 6.1, 3</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it doth neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily implie that there muſt be Magiſtrates, &amp; praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And herein is fulfilled that prophecie of <hi>Eſ.</hi> 66.21. concerning the <hi>Miniſterie</hi> of the N. T. I will take of them for Prieſts, and for Levites, ſaith the Lord. (<hi>i.e.</hi>) Though the <hi>diſtinction of Tribes</hi> bee taken away, and that old Prieſthood ceaſed, yet God promiſed it as a bleſſing to the Church of the Gentiles, that hee would raiſ up of themſelvs ſom that ſhould bee in ſtead of the old Prieſts and Levites, in things pertein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe undeniable proofs, I frame theſe 3 Arguments, as to the main cauſ.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>1</label> 1. Look how the Apoſtles <hi>did ordain,</hi> and call Miniſters of the Word, and as they <hi>appointed</hi> others after them to bee ordained and ſent, ſo and in like manner, ought men now to bee ſent and ordained. But the Apoſtles <hi>did</hi> ordain men for the miniſtration of the word and ſacraments by laying on of hands, and alſo <hi>appointed</hi> and enjoined the ſame to bee <hi>don</hi> in the Churches of Chriſt—therefore it is Chriſt's Ordinance, that ſo it ought ſtill to bee don, and they that do otherwiſe do go againſt the example and appointment of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and ſo overthrow an Ordinance of Chriſt in the N. Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>2</label> 2. That which is <hi>contrarie to the examples, rules and directions</hi> of Scripture, cannot bee don without ſin. —But to adminiſter the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40677:9"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> word or ſacraments without Ordination is <hi>contrarie</hi> to the examples and rules of Scripture; therefore it is unlawful, and cannot bee don without ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>3</label> 3. If <hi>Sending bee more then Gifting</hi> (by God's word) then there is ſomthing <hi>more</hi> by God's word required unto preaching, then ſole Gifting: —But <hi>Sending</hi> is, according to God's word, <hi>more</hi> then Gifting, therefore ſomthing more then Gifting is required to make a preacher of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Sending is more then Gifting,</hi> is evident, becauſ Gifted men muſt bee ordained. <hi>Timothie</hi> was a man rarely Gifted, yet hee was ordained and ſent by the outward calling of the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. and ſo were the reſt of whom wee read, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2, 3.</p>
            <p>There bee two things required to make a <hi>Miniſter.</hi> 1. Gifts, which muſt bee tried and approved. 2. Ordination and ſolemn Inauguration into their Office. <hi>Gifts</hi> give not <hi>Autoritie</hi> to any man for any thing; the <hi>Lawyer</hi> at the Bar may have as great gifts as the Judg upon the Bench, yet becauſ-hee hath not the like Commiſſion, hee may not intrude upon the Judges office. A private man may bee as <hi>well Gifted</hi> as a Juſtice of Peace, yet, without a Commiſſion, hee may not do his office; ſo is it in this preſent caſe.</p>
            <p>There is but one branch of the ſecond Concluſion unproved, which ſaith that Ordination muſt bee by the <hi>laying of hands of other Miniſters,</hi> and this is added to put a difference between true and falſ Ordination: In ſom congregational Churches, they have their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors ordained (i.e.) choſen and appointed by the people: Truely then they may preach and exerciſe <hi>Miniſteriall Acts</hi> in the name of the <hi>People,</hi> but not in the <hi>name of Chriſt,</hi> unleſs they did derive their Autoritie by Ordination from Chriſt.</p>
            <p>It is a groſs miſtake to think or teach that <hi>Church-power is Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> in the People, as the <hi>proper ſeat</hi> and ſubject thereof, from them to bee derived and placed upon whom they chooſ: Chriſt gave all power to the Bodie of the Church <hi>finaliter &amp; objectivè</hi> (i e.) for their uſe and benefit, according to that of the Apoſtle. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. All things are <hi>yours,</hi> whether <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> all are <hi>yours, i.e. for your ſervice and ſalvation,</hi> but they <hi>are not yours, i.e.</hi> they are <hi>not of your making and autorizing:</hi> Church-power is <hi>firſt ſeated</hi> in Chriſt the Head and Apoſtle of our poſſeſſion, and from him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Apoſtles, and from them to Biſhops and other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40677:9"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> ſters by ſucceſſion: they <hi>commit the ſame to others</hi> which themſelvs had firſt received, but (according to that known rule) <hi>no man can give to another, that which himſelf hath not firſt received,</hi> therefore the people which <hi>never received Orders, nor Power</hi> to adminiſter the word, ſacraments, and keies, how they can can beſtow it on others, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all Scripture and reaſon: <hi>Church-power</hi> is in the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church by <hi>Derivation</hi> from the Apoſtles, and <hi>they alone</hi> can commit, and <hi>Tranſmit it unto others.</hi> The Text is expreſs which ſaith, that Ordination is by the hands of the presbyterie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But how can you can juſtifie your calling to the Miniſterie, ſeeing you were ordained by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and Biſhops from the Pope, and the Pope is from the devil. You loſt your <hi>true ſucceſsion</hi> in the Papacie, and the calling which yee <hi>now have,</hi> is <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> The Papiſts ſay, wee have no true Miniſterie, becauſ at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation wee <hi>received it not from Rome.</hi> The Browniſts ſay our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are not rightly called into their Offices, becauſ wee r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eived it from <hi>Rome.</hi> Thus wee are condemned of all hands, one of theſe accuſers muſt needs charge us falſly, but admit both their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to have ſom truth, yet neither of them do conclude what they intend.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To anſwer the Papiſt, I ſhall onely crave leav to inſert among my plain pages, a letter of that moſt godly learned man, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Reinolds</hi> to a friend of his, who craved his help to anſwer the challenge of ſom Papiſts touching the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of our Miniſterie.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Your godly requſt (good M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Barker</hi>) I ſhould bee ſomwhat better able to ſatisfie,<note place="margin">Dr Rainolds his Letter.</note> if I knew on what grounds theſe proud popiſh challengers do perſwade themſelvs that none of you can avow your vocation to the Miniſterie to bee lawful. But I gueſs they do it on the ſame, that <hi>Hart</hi> in his conference with mee, becauſ the ancient Canons Eccleſiaſtical aſcribed to the Apoſtles ſay, <hi>Epiſcopus duobus aut tribus Epiſcopis ordinetur, Presbyter autem ab uno Epiſcopo:</hi> and they think none of us to bee ordained by a Biſhop, becauſ in the beginning of her Majeſties reign, one popiſh Biſhop of Q. <hi>Maries</hi> beeing then left, none of our Biſhops could bee ordained by two or three. Now if they build hereupon (as to mee it ſeemeth they do, becauſ I finde no other reaſon in<note n="b" place="margin">Decler. c. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Epitom. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov. part. <hi>1.</hi> Con. <hi>4.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Parſons,</hi> or<note n="d" place="margin">Harding, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton, Greg de Valem.</note> the reſt, of this objection againſt us) it may bee, that as <hi>Hart,</hi> when hee ſaw the anſwer that I made thereunto, would needs have that whole point left out in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40677:10"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>2</label> ſaying hee would not preſs mee therewith; ſo theſe men will renounce their promiſs of ſubſcribing to the profeſſion of the Goſpel, and forſaking Poperie, when they ſee you able to juſtifie your calling to the Miniſterie. For I went to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> his Regiſter, and taking thence a note how Biſhop <hi>Freak</hi> (who ordained mee) <hi>conſecratus eſt à Matthaeo Cant. Roberto Winton. &amp; Edmundo Sarum;</hi> and how each of theſe was conſecrated by other three or four, as <hi>Matthaeus Cant.</hi> by four that were Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, theſe again conſecrated by Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> (whom three with the Pope's conſent had conſecrated) and ſo brought every one upward to thoſe times wherein the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> acknowledged them ordained lawfully, I had no ſooner ſhewed this extract to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Hart,</hi> but hee confeſſed hee thought no ſuch thing could bee ſhewed, and that himſelf had been born in hand otherwiſe, on the conceit above mentioned. You, who are further from <hi>London,</hi> where the records are kept (though your friend if need bee, can help you thereunto) may ask them, if they think not Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and the reſt in King <hi>Henrie's</hi> time, to bee lawfully ordained Biſhops, which when they acknowledg (becauſ the Pope confirmed them) you may offer this proof, that our Biſhops ſucceeding them in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time, and ſo in Q. <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> were conſecrated by three of them, or their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fors, out of the authentical Records of the Archbiſhoprick, <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>il.</hi> that <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> the firſt Archbiſhop in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> daies, was thus by <hi>William Barlow,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells</hi> in K. <hi>Edward's</hi> time, <hi>John Scorie</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter, Miles Coverdale</hi> of <hi>Exeter, John Hodgeskir</hi> Suffragane of <hi>Bedford.</hi> If they acknowledg that hee and all the reſt in like ſort were conſecrated by a number of Biſhops ſufficient, but theſe not confirmed by the Pope, as the firſt in King <hi>Henrie</hi>'s time were, they muſt bring forth proof that without his conſent no Biſhop is lawfully ordained, which ſoundly they never can. If they ſay the Biſhops ſince <hi>Cranmer</hi>'s time, were and are Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and therefore are not lawfully autorized to ordain; firſt here they will fail in proof too, becauſ Hereſie is an error repugnant to the word of God, and that wee hold any ſuch, they cannot ſhew: then admitting the contrarie, and putting the caſe wee did, to avoid ſo huge debate of all points in controverſie, their own Principal Doctors,<note n="a" place="margin">In <hi>4.</hi> ſent. diſt. <hi>25.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi> Con. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Dominicus Soto,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">De ſacram. in genere, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Com. Theal. Tom. <hi>4</hi> diſt <hi>9.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> puncts <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Greg. de Valentia,</hi> do teach out of S.<note n="d" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> contr. epiſtolam Parmén. tract. <hi>9.</hi> in Evang. Joannis, Jo. <hi>9.33.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> grounding on the Scripture, that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40677:10"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>2</label> Biſhops may lawfully Ordain, and that it is an hereſie, ſuch as the <hi>Dontatiſts</hi> was, to denie it. What other cavils or ſophiſms they are likely to uſe, I cannot imagine, but very willing to yield you any help that I can, upon farther notice, I commend you to the Grace of our good God, beſeeching him to direct and ſtrengthen by his holy Spirit, your ſelf, and the reſt of your fellow Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to fight his Battels.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>At Oxford</hi> 
                        <date>the third of June. 1605.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>JOHN RAINOLDS,</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>IF any doubt of this Letter, he may receiv ſatisfaction touching the Truth of it by ſom yet living in <hi>Corpus Chriſti Colledg,</hi> from whom I had this Copie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But though this ſtop the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> mouth, yet it <hi>ſtrengthen's</hi> the other part of the Objection, with whom wee have chiefly to deal.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Not at all: 1 For though our Conſecration and Succeſſion were <hi>continued</hi> in the times of the Pop's reign, yet it did not fetch its <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal</hi> from the Pope: the Goſpel ſounded out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the Word of the Lord from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> even as far as <hi>Britain long enough before</hi> that Anti-chriſt of <hi>Rome</hi> was born.<note place="margin">Rom. 16.26. Col. 1.6.</note> And though wee ſhould not think the worſ of the Goſpel though received from <hi>Rome</hi> in her firſt pure ſtate (whom <hi>Paul</hi> celebrate's for a famous Church.)<note place="margin">Rom. 1.6, 8. Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noments, l. 2. p. 1. &amp;c. Whites way to the Church § 49.</note> Yet the light came to <hi>England</hi> firſt from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and not from <hi>Rome,</hi> as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Fox</hi> and D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John White</hi> have learnedly demonſtrated out of <hi>Gildas</hi> and ſundrie other Autors, who affirm that <hi>Britain</hi> received the Goſpel in the time of <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperor, under whom Chriſt was crucified; and though there bee ſom little variance among Autors about the time, yet that confirm's the Truth of the matter in which they all concur, that <hi>England</hi> received the Goſpel <hi>very early,</hi> either by the preaching of ſom one of the Apoſtles or ſom of that time: moſtly received is, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> was ſent by <hi>Philip</hi> from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Britain,</hi> about the year 63. and laid the firſt foundation of the Chriſtian Faith, which was confirmed and increaſed by others.</p>
            <p>The ſame is confirmed by the Teſtimonie of <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Adverſus Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daees c. <hi>7.</hi> Et Britannorum inacceſſa Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca, Chriſts verò ſuhdita.</note> in his Book againſt the Jews, where reckoning the <hi>parts</hi> of the world, whither the Goſpel was diſperſed by the ſound of the Apoſtles, reciteth the parts of <hi>Britain</hi> unſubdued by the Romane's ſword, yet ſubdued unto the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40677:11"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>2</label> Scepter of Chriſt. 2. Again, the ſame M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Fox</hi> relateth that about the year 180, King <hi>Lucius</hi> (the firſt Chriſtned King) ſent to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to receiv of him the Chriſtian Faith [others ſay to receiv <hi>farther inſtructions</hi> from him.] <hi>Eleutherius</hi> ſent unto him <hi>Damianus</hi> and <hi>Faganus,</hi> by whom the King was converted, with many of the people, and were baptized about the year 179 the Monumentsand Rites of Heatheniſh Idolatrie were ſubverted, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition decaied, and true Religion increaſed; there were then in <hi>Britain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fox Acts &amp; Mon. ubiſupra.</note> 28 Head Prieſts which they called <hi>Flamines,</hi> and three Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſts, which they called <hi>Arch-Flamines,</hi> having the <hi>over-ſight of the manners over the reſt.</hi> Theſe 28 <hi>Flamines</hi> they turned to 28 Biſhops, and the three <hi>Arch-Flamines</hi> to three Arch-biſhopricks having then their Seats in three principal Cities, <hi>viz. London, York, Glouceſter.</hi> In theſe daies, <hi>Rome</hi> was a <hi>Virgin Church</hi> not Anti-Chriſtian. And if wee grant that <hi>England</hi> received the Faith from <hi>Eleutherius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet hee was <hi>neither a Pope nor Papiſt.</hi> And from this <hi>Apoſtolical root</hi> do wee extract our Ordination and Succeſſion, as beeing well aſſured that very early in the Primitive Church,<note place="margin">Whites Way to the Church, § 49.</note> the Goſpel was planted here. And though the Papiſts object that the Faith was again extinguiſhed in <hi>England,</hi> yet D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>White</hi> ſhew's the contrarie, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Faith continued here from King <hi>Lucius</hi> to the coming of <hi>Auſten</hi> the Monk, whom <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſent hither 600 years after Chriſt, who when hee came <hi>found divers Brittain Biſhops</hi> and learned men, with a monaſterie at <hi>Bangor,</hi> who did oppoſe <hi>Arrianiſm</hi> and <hi>Pelagianiſm,</hi> and the <hi>pride</hi> of <hi>Auſten</hi> the Pope's Embaſſador.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſay, that the <hi>rightfulneſs</hi> of our Vocation is not <hi>cut off, or nulled by ſuch a Succeſſion;</hi> for that learned Letter as it confeſſeth the Succeſſion of our firſt Reformers to have been from men of the Romiſh Religion,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.2.3.</note> ſo it teacheth truly, That <hi>Heretical Biſhops may lawfully Ordain, and that it is an Hereſie, ſuch as the Donatiſh was to denie it.</hi> To this agree's the judgment of our Saviour, who Teacheth that the Scribes and Phariſees have a <hi>lawful Succeſſion from Moſes,</hi> (they ſit in his Chair, their Calling is of God) though a <hi>race of bad men</hi> poſſeſſed that Chair, and Chriſt will have them <hi>acknowledged</hi> for the lawful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. So is our Calling and Succeſſion, though it paſſed thorough corrupt times: The <hi>Scriptures themſelvs, Baptiſm, &amp; the Articles of our Creed,</hi> have all paſſed through the Papacie unto us, and yet they ceaſ not to bee <hi>true Scriptures, nor true Baptiſm;</hi> much leſs doe's Ordination ceaſ to be rightful, it beeing an act of <hi>juriſdiction,</hi> which may bee legally and law fully performed by men of corrupt Faith.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40677:11"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>2</label> Wee muſt carefully <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> the <hi>Acts of Office</hi> [which have their form and beeing from a root or fountain without us] from the <hi>qualities of the man,</hi> that perform's the Office. The man may bee naught, yet his Office good; and <hi>Acts don by virtue</hi> of his Office juſt and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable, although the man and his Religion bee naught. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Landlord make's you a <hi>Leaſ</hi> of a Farm, your Leaſ is not Antichriſtian, but <hi>good in Law,</hi> though hee that demiſed it, bee for his Religion, a Papiſt. A Popiſh Judg doth paſs a <hi>ſentence</hi> in Court, which ſtand's good in Judicature: <hi>His ſentence</hi> is not Popiſh, though hee that pronounced it bee a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> the reaſon is, becauſ the <hi>legal ſentence is not of him,</hi> nor from him, as a Papiſt, but a Judg, who doth but deliver that which hee hath received from <hi>an higher root the Law;</hi> So in this caſe, Ordination is an <hi>Act of Office</hi> derived from Chriſt, and it is not Popiſh though executed by a Papiſt. Wee do not rebaptize them that were baptized by a Popiſh Prieſt, becauſ the <hi>power of Ged's Ordinance</hi> depend's not on the perſon that doe's execute the ſame, but upon an higher foundation, the Inſtitution of Chriſt. Miniſterial Acts are not vitiated or made <hi>nud,</hi> though they paſs through the hands of bad men; But ſtand good to all intents and purpoſes to <hi>ſuch as receiv them aright,</hi> by virtue of their Office <hi>autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively</hi> derived from the firſt Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>To <hi>right</hi> Ordination (beſides the parties inward Call) are required,<note place="margin">To right Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination what is requited.</note> Two things: 1. On behalf of the <hi>partie to bee Ordained,</hi> hee muſt have ſundrie qualifications, as integritie of life by which hee get's a <hi>good report</hi> even of thoſe that are without: 2. Soundneſs in the Faith, hee muſt not bee an <hi>Heretick</hi> or misbeliever, but able by ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to inſtruct and convince the gain-faier: 3. Hee muſt bee apt to teach, readie to communicate his knowledg to others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, on behalf of them that <hi>do ordain,</hi> it is likewiſe required; 1. That they <hi>take a trial</hi> of their Gifts and Life, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Let them firſt bee proved and then let them miniſter if they bee ſound worthie. 2. Then follow's <hi>Ordination</hi> it ſelf, which is don, when then they are <hi>Conſecrated and ſet apart, and Autorized</hi> with impoſition of hands and praier to preach the Word in the Name of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. 3. Then follow's their <hi>Election or deſignation</hi> to their particular places and charges, which is don, <hi>partly</hi> by the voice of the people, <hi>and partly</hi> by the wiſdom of the Guides of the Church.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>are wee</hi> Qualified, Called, Admitted and Autorized to execute the ſacred Function, according to Scirpture-Rules, and God hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40677:12"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>2</label>
               <hi>ſealed to us the fruit of our Calling,</hi> by the converſion of many thouſand ſouls, in Chriſt Jeſus wee by the bleſſing and aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt have begotten you, ſo that if wee bee not true Miniſters of Chriſt to others, yet ſurely wee are to the people of this Nation, and to ſom, (wee hope) of our preſent, though <hi>uuthankful and Cauſleſs</hi> enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But private men unordained may convert ſouls, as the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> informed her neighbors, <hi>Rahab</hi> was converted by the Spies, <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>priſcilla</hi> helped <hi>Apollos,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> I ſhall Anſwer this point more largely under my laſt concluſion, for this preſent thus: I doubt not but much good is don by the faithful reproofs, counſels and inſtructions of private Chriſtians; women may ſave their husbands,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.16. 1 Pet. 3.1. Tit. 2.3.</note> at leaſt win them to a liking of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie; the Elder women muſt bee Teacher's of good things, and ſo the Members of the Church do edifie one another: But what? is this Chriſt's Ordinarie way? muſt this overthrow Chriſt's Order and Ordinance? No, by no means. If any of you bee <hi>inwardly toucht</hi> with the zeal of God's glorie, with a <hi>ſenſ</hi> of the peoples ignorance and miſerie, let ſuch beeing tried, and found <hi>Orthodox and competently gifted,</hi> bee Ordained. Let them give themſelvs to this work, and wee will <hi>give them</hi> the right <hi>hand of fellowſhip,</hi> without asking, of what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie</hi> they were. But beware how yee bring diſorder and confuſion into the Church, and ſo overthrow the Ordinance of Chriſt, upon ſerious conſideration of our third Concluſion which now followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label> Having proved in the fomer Concluſions, that the Work of the Miniſterie is an <hi>Office appointed</hi> of God, and that <hi>Ordination</hi> for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting that Office is an Ordinance of Chriſt in the New Teſtament our third Concluſion will naturally follow, <hi>viz. That no man uncalled and unordained can, with good conſcience intrude upon that work and Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This poſition or Concluſion is proved by two places eſpecially remarkable for this purpoſe, the firſt is that of <hi>Zach.</hi> 83.3, 4, 5. And it ſhall com to paſs—that the Prophets ſhall bee aſhamed every one of his Viſion when hee hath propheſied, neither ſhall they wear a rough garment to deceiv, but hee ſhall ſay, I am no Prophet, I am an husbandman, for man taught mee to keep Cattel from my youth. 1. This place is a <hi>plain Prophecie</hi> of the times of the Goſpel, wherein many bleſſings are promiſed when the Meſſiah is com, <hi>verſ</hi> 1.2.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40677:12"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label> 2. The words, <hi>verſ</hi> 4.5. are <hi>words of Recantation</hi> and repentance of ſom that pretended the Spirit, and took upon them the Office of Propheſying, when as they were not Prophets, but husbandmen, or bred up to ſom other Trades. 3. The <hi>means by which</hi> this kind of Teachers were brought to ſhame and repentance, is the zeal of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate upon complaint made to him of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings by their <hi>dearest</hi> friends, <hi>verſ</hi> 3. And it ſhall com to paſs, that when any ſhall yet Prophecie, <hi>i.e.</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>all ſpiritual</hi> means uſed to cleanſ the Land of ſeducing ſpirits and Teachers of falſ Doctrines, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.) if for all this, they ſhall prophecie, then his Father and his Mother which begat him, ſhall ſay unto him, Thou ſhalt not live, &amp;c. the meaning is this, that as in the Law of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 13.5, 8. Hee that pretended himſelf a Prophet and was <hi>none,</hi> was to bee puniſhed by the Magiſtrate: ſuch a like zeal ſhould bee uſed againſt falſ Prophets in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> their beſt friends endued with knowledg and diſcerning, ſhall <hi>oppoſe</hi> them, preferring their zeal and pietie towards God, before the natural affection they bear towards their own children. And there is reaſon (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Borough's</hi> thinks) why their <hi>best friends</hi> ſhould withſtand them in this way: <q>1. Becauſ it is a thing abhorring to Nature,<note place="margin">Heart-diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, p. 19.23.24.</note> that men ſhould ſuffer God whom they honor, to bee blaſphemed. 2. To ſee their wives and children, and deareſt friends to bee <hi>ſeduced</hi> into waies which wee think will undo their ſouls to eternitie, and not bee able to help them nor our ſelvs, unleſs wee can perſwade the Seducer to deſiſt, and ask them why they do ſo, and entreat them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear:</q> Therefore theſe muſt com under the <hi>Magiſtrates reſtraining power.</hi> 4. Then follow's the <hi>fruit</hi> of the Magiſtrates dealing with them, <hi>viz. Their ſhame and repentance,</hi> they ſhall diſclaim their <hi>uſurped profeſſion,</hi> and confeſs that they were never brought up, nor fitted for it, and ſo return to their former courſ and <hi>Trade</hi> of living. This Scripture is fulfilled in <hi>one part,</hi> by the <hi>riſing of falſ</hi> Teachers in our daies, and if it bee not fulfilled in the other part, <hi>viz. in their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> one principal cauſ thereof, is, becauſ our Magiſtrates are ſo far from putting them to ſhame, that they rather <hi>uphold them,</hi> having <hi>enfranchized</hi> every Sect to hold Aſſemblies <hi>to preach who will;</hi> yea, to the <hi>diſadvantage</hi> of Chriſt's Goſpel, have <hi>ſuffered</hi> his Miniſters to bee <hi>vilified</hi> &amp; reproched even in <hi>Almanacks,</hi> and to bee made the ſcorn and deriſion of the raging waves of the Sea, and mocking ſpirits, of which S. <hi>Jude</hi> complains, <hi>v.</hi> 13.18. I pray God this bee not laid to their charge.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40677:13"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> Our ſecond place is, <hi>Num.</hi> 16.1, 2, 3, 5. <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> were Gentlemen of the Tribe of <hi>Reuben</hi> the eldeſt ſon of <hi>Jacob, Num.</hi> 26. 5, 9. This is that <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> which were famous in the Congregation, they thought they had as <hi>much right to the Government</hi> as <hi>Moſes,</hi> who came of a yonger Tribe, and therefore [like Levellers] they ſay to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> wherefore lift you up your ſelvs above the Congregation of the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. And when they were ſummoned to appear before <hi>Moſes,</hi> they refuſed, ſaying, wee will not com, <hi>verſ</hi> 12.13. Is it a ſmall thing that thou haſt brought us out of a Land flowing with milk and honie, except thou <hi>make they ſelf altogether a Prince</hi> over us? their <hi>quarrel</hi> was eſpecially againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> againſt the <hi>Civil Power. Korah</hi> for his part was a <hi>Levite,</hi> and hee would have <hi>none above him</hi> in the Church, hee would needs do the office of a Prieſt as well as <hi>Aaron;</hi> ſeek yee the <hi>Prieſthood alſo,</hi> (ſaies <hi>Moſes</hi> to him, <hi>v.</hi> 10.) His quarrel was <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> againſt <hi>Aaron, verſ</hi> 11. What is <hi>Aaron</hi> that yee murmur againſt him? Thus yee ſee how <hi>Korah</hi> did endevor to make <hi>common the Offices</hi> of the Prieſthood, and why? becauſ (ſaid hee) <hi>all the Congregation</hi> of the Lord is holy, <hi>verſ</hi> 3. <hi>All have the gifts of the Spirit;</hi> as if God's Ordinarie gifts of <hi>Sanctification,</hi> did take away <hi>diſtinction of Callings</hi> and Offices: But what ſaies <hi>Moſes</hi> to all this geer? <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. To morrow the Lord will ſhew <hi>who are his and who is holy,</hi> and will cauſ him to com near unto him, <hi>i.e.</hi> God will, <hi>by miracle ſhew whom hee accepteth for his ſervant in the Government, you or mee:</hi> And who is <hi>holy, i.e.</hi> whom hee hath <hi>conſecrated</hi> to com near unto him by ſpecial Calling to do the Office of a Prieſt, <hi>Aaron or you.</hi> All the Congregation is <hi>holy,</hi> by the Gift of <hi>common vocation</hi> unto Grace, but not by <hi>ſpecial Gift of conſecration</hi> to the Office of a Prieſt. As <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7. ſaith, that the Husband is the <hi>image</hi> of God in reſpect of <hi>domeſtick Autoritie;</hi> the wife is the image of God in reſpect of the <hi>gifts of grace,</hi> as well as her Husband; but the Husband, and ſo every good Magiſtrate hath on him a <hi>twofold image</hi> of God: 1. One by gifts of Grace <hi>common</hi> with other Saints. 2. The other by <hi>ſpecial Calling</hi> and Autoritie to his Office in Church or State.</p>
            <p>Well, you ſee <hi>Korah's ſin</hi> what it is; but how doe's the Lord take this at his hands? ſee <hi>v.</hi> 35. Thoſe 250 men which offered incenſ and <hi>invaded</hi> the holy Office, were burnt to death with fire from Heaven. And for a <hi>Monument</hi> to all Poſteritie, that None who is not Called and Conſecrated, ſhould preſume to take upon him the Office of <hi>miniſtring holy things,</hi> to make himſelf near to God in theſe peculiar
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40677:13"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> Services, God commanded the Cenſers, wherewith they had offered the Incenſ, to bee kept for a <hi>memorial</hi> unto the children of <hi>Iſraël,</hi> that no <hi>ſtranger,</hi> which is not of the ſeed of <hi>Aaron,</hi> com near to offer Incenſ before the Lord, that hee bee not as <hi>Korah</hi> and his Companie, <hi>verſ.</hi> 40. Alſo God commanded <hi>Aarons</hi> rod that budded, to bee kept for a <hi>token againſt the Rebels,</hi> and thou ſhalt quite take away their murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>Num.</hi> 17.10. And they ſhall know that whoſoëver com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>near</hi> to the Tabernacle of the Lord, without a Calling to do the Office of a Prieſt, is <hi>in danger to die,</hi> as <hi>Korah</hi> did <hi>verſ</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>But what is this to us? In the Old Teſtament God had preciſely limited the Prieſts Office to <hi>one Tribe,</hi> how doe's this reaſon hold in the New Teſtament?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The application hereof is made by S. <hi>Jude, verſ</hi> 11. To the times of the New Teſtament. Wo unto them, for they have ran greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for reward, and <hi>are periſhed in the gain-ſaying of Korah:</hi> Hence I thus argue, <hi>If the ſin</hi> of <hi>Korah</hi> is, and may bee <hi>committed in the New Teſtament,</hi> then it follows undeniably, that in the New Teſtament it is a ſin to <hi>level Church-Offices,</hi> or intrude into the actions of <hi>ſacred Miniſterie,</hi> whereto one is not Called, leaſt hee periſh in <hi>Korah</hi>'s ſin.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle S. <hi>Jude</hi> fore-telling what Sectaries then were, and ſhould bee in Chriſt's Church, and ſetting them out by certain <hi>characters</hi> by which they might bee known among others, hath this, <hi>verſ</hi> 11. That they are <hi>guiltie of Korah's gain-ſaying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words <hi>I note three things:</hi> Firſt, that the ſin of <hi>Korah</hi> is and may bee <hi>committed</hi> in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That <hi>none can</hi> commit the ſin of <hi>Korah</hi> under the New Teſtament, if there were not a <hi>Diſtinction</hi> and <hi>reſervation</hi> of miniſterial Offices and Autorities to men ſet apart for that work, as in <hi>Korah's</hi> time.)</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That thoſe of whom <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks, are <hi>therefore guiltie of Korah's</hi> ſin, becauſ they <hi>invaded</hi> the Office of the <hi>Goſpel-Miniſterie</hi> [for now wee have no <hi>proper Prieſts nor ſacrifices</hi>] as <hi>Korah</hi> did <hi>the Office of the Prieſthood</hi> under the Law: That old Prieſthood is changed, Chriſt hath erected another Miniſterie in their ſtead, which muſt bee <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved inviolable</hi> from all invaders, as that of <hi>Aarons</hi> was, for elſ the ſin of <hi>Korah</hi> could not bee committed in the times of the New Teſtament. But ſeeing the ſin of <hi>Korah</hi> is committed under the New Teſtament. our concluſion ſtand's good, that it is a ſin for men <hi>uncalled</hi> to exerciſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40677:14"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label> the Office of the <hi>Goſpel Miniſtrie</hi> or of a Prophet being bred up to feed Cattel, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto, for cloſe of all, that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4, 5. No man taketh this honor to himſelf, but hee that is Called of God, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was.<note place="margin">1 Kin. 12.35. with c. 13.33.</note> It was a ſin in <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to make Prieſts of the <hi>loweſt</hi> of the people, which <hi>were not of the Tribe of Levi:</hi> When <hi>Jeroboam</hi> revolted from the Houſ of <hi>David,</hi> hee <hi>changed the worſhip and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 11.13.</note>(the honeſt Miniſterie were not for his turn) leaſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould return to their dutie, but God curſed this devilliſh policie, for this thing <hi>became ſin to the Houſ</hi> of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to cut it off, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it from the face of the earth: As then, ſo <hi>now it is a ſin</hi> for any man to take that honor to himſelf: The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> words are <hi>general</hi> and <hi>Argumentative</hi> to this ſenſ, becauſ no man ought to intrude into this holy Office without a Calling, therefore neither might Chriſt; if a man take an Office, not appointed of God thereunto, it is no honor to him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſ. </seg>
               </label> No man can <hi>make himſelf a Steward or Embaſſador,</hi> no man can do any thing in God's Houſ, as <hi>his Steward or Embaſſador to preach his Covenant and ſet thereto God's ſeal,</hi> but they that have <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from God. Now a Commiſſion is the <hi>imparting</hi> of a power to us, which <hi>before</hi> wee had not. By <hi>virtue</hi> of God's Commiſſion wee are Stewards of God and Embaſſadors for Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. Chriſt hath <hi>committed to us</hi> the word of reconciliation, and <hi>wee in his Name and with his Autoritie</hi> do <hi>tender and ſeal God's Covenant:</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God's Commiſſion, all ſacred actions are meer <hi>nullities and mockeries,</hi> like a <hi>Judgment</hi> without a <hi>Juriſdiction;</hi> of no more Autoritie, then if a private perſon ſhould give ſentence upon the Bench, or Mid-wife Baptize your Children: The Phariſes queſtioned <hi>John</hi> for baptizing, <hi>Job</hi> 1.25. And Chriſt for Preaching, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.23. The Prieſts and Elders of the people came to him as <hi>hee was Teaching,</hi> and ſaid, by what <hi>Autoritie</hi> doſt thou theſe things, and who gave thee this Autoritie? Chriſt doe's yield the challenge to bee juſt, if hee could not have <hi>ſhewed his Autoritie,</hi> and therefore in his Anſwer, Chriſt doth avouch both <hi>Johns</hi> and <hi>his own Miniſterie</hi> to bee from Heaven, <hi>verſ</hi> 2.25. The Apoſtle is clear, that God is the <hi>Autor, who ſel's the ordinarie Pastors and Teachers</hi> in the Church,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.28.</note> as <hi>well as</hi> the Apoſtles and Prophets, and <hi>without his ſetting,</hi> wee can no more do the Office of Paſtors and Teachers <hi>then of Apoſtles.</hi> Wee muſt <hi>attend</hi> God's Calling to God's imploiment.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40677:14"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label> For the premiſes, I conclude in the words of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hooker.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hooker</hi> Pol. 5. § 77.</note> 
               <q>The Miniſterie of Divine things is a <hi>function</hi> which as God did himſelf Inſtitute, ſo neither may man undertake the ſame but by Autoritie and Power given them in lawful manner—They are therefore Miniſters of God, not onely by way of <hi>Subordination,</hi> as Princes and Civil Magiſtrates are, whoſe execution of Judgment and Juſtice, the ſupreme hand of divine providence doth uphold, but Miniſters of God, as <hi>from whom</hi> their Autoritie is derived <hi>and not from men:</hi> For in that they are <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> and his laborers, who can give them their Commiſſion, but hee <hi>whoſe moſt inward affairs they manage?</hi> Is not God alone the Father of ſpirits? Are not ſouls the purchaſe of Jeſus Chriſt? What Angel in Heaven could have ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> Feed my ſheep? preach, baptize, do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of mee, whoſe ſins yee retain they are retained, and whoſe yee remit, they are remitted? What think yee, are theſe <hi>terreſtrial ſouls?</hi> the power of the Miniſterie of God tranſlateth out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into glorie, it doth diſpoſe of that fleſh which was given for the life of the World, and it poureth malediction upon the heads of the wicked.—The <hi>things wee do,</hi> ſhew that wee are and can bee Commiſſioned by <hi>none but Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> All the Princes of the world cannot give us this Autoritie and Commiſſion, wee cannot bee <hi>Deputies in theſe Divine things,</hi> becauſ themſelvs have not the chief power to <hi>diſpence the things in perſon,</hi> nor to <hi>beſtow</hi> the bleſſings and curſes at their will and command, whereof wee are made the Inſtruments.</q> What impudence then is it for Mechanicks who have received Commiſſion neither from God nor man, <hi>to intrude into this Office?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Som have ſaid, What <hi>evil</hi> is it for gifted men to preach though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called, mee thinks they do well, better then your drie dunces of the Clergie, they hold forth Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Wee envie no mans gifts, wee diminiſh them not, onely wee plead for Chriſt's Ordinance: Let them ſubmit to Chriſt's Ordinance to bee tried and Ordained and then Preach and ſpare not; elſ there's evil enough in ſuch under-takings, judg with equitie. 1. <hi>What evil</hi> is it for a private man to <hi>execute the office</hi> of a Conſtable? to <hi>pull a Judg from the Bench?</hi> mee thinks hee doe's better reform manners and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vice, then your old rotten Magiſtrates: muſt wee <hi>ſtay</hi> for a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> when things bee amiſs? <hi>Abſalom</hi> will miniſter juſtice better then his Father <hi>David;</hi> aie, by all means; things are like to go well,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40677:15"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> if every man that reckon's himſelf gifted, may bee <hi>judg what is best,</hi> and <hi>himſelf the fitteſt</hi> to do it. But God is a God of Order, Unitie, Peace, and not of Confuſion. 2. And this I dare affirm, that the Devil hath not a more ſubtil <hi>prevalent engine</hi> to pull down the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, and ſet up his own [which is eſtabliſht by Hereſie, Sedition, Falſ-worſhip, Envie, Hatred, Schiſm, Diſſention, &amp;c.] then by <hi>deſtroying the Miniſterie</hi> whereby God hath erected and built his Church: But as long as Chriſt will have a Church among us, hee will hold thoſe <hi>ſtars in his right hand;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1.16, 20.</note> And whenſoëver you ſee them pluckt out of the Firmament of the Church,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.41, 42 2 Chro. 36.16.</note> then look for nothing but a <hi>ſad night</hi> of darkneſs and miſerie upon this Nation: They are the greateſt <hi>malignants</hi> and avowed enemies of our Nation, that are haters of it's <hi>Miniſterie.</hi> But let them beware what they do, for if hee that <hi>loveth</hi> and receiveth a Prophet in the name of a Prophet,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 10 41.</note> ſhall receiv a Prophet's reward, then hee that <hi>deſpiſeth,</hi> derideth, hateth, vilifieth a Prophet in the <hi>name</hi> of a Prophet, or becauſ hee is a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of the Goſpel, hee carrie's in his <hi>breaſt</hi> the mark of a Reprobate, and let him bee ſure that hee ſhall receiv the reward of a Prophet-hater.</p>
            <p>The truth is, God hath made <hi>theſe Preachers a check, a ſhame,</hi> and <hi>a juſt rebuke</hi> to a rotten,<note place="margin">See Mal. 2.3, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>formal, dead Clergie,</hi> that underſtood not, nor ever endeavored the converſion of ſouls; God would by a fooliſh people <hi>provoke</hi> men of abilities to a more ſpiritual and conſcionable diſcharge of their duties, <hi>'twere good</hi> this uſe were made of it; But what <hi>good</hi> elſ this promiſcuous preaching hath don, how it hath advanced truth or godlineſs, is their part to ſhew. What <hi>miſchief</hi> it hath don, what <hi>Errors</hi> it hath ſpread, how many <hi>unſtable</hi> ſouls it hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled, what fearful Schiſms and Factions it hath brought into our Land, what <hi>diſcord</hi> among brethren, &amp;c. There bee too many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in moſt Counties of <hi>England.</hi> By ſuch like men, you ſee what preaching you are like to have, if ever your eſtabliſht Miniſterie bee extinguiſhed. People by degrees will grow to a <hi>loathing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> of the Goſpel preached, through their prophaning it with their <hi>fulſom</hi> fooleries.</p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe up this point with a remarkable paſſage of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Owens</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Toleration,</hi> joined with <hi>that Sermon of his,</hi> which hee preached before the Houſ, <hi>Jan.</hi> 31. 1648.—His words are theſe: <q>There are a ſort of perſons termed in Scripture <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> unruly, diſorderly,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Owen</hi> of Toleration, p. 82.</note> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>baſer ſort, Act.</hi> 17.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40677:15"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label>
                  <hi>abſurd,</hi> unreaſonable men, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>lawleſs and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. and the like diſorderly, vagabond, wandring, irregular perſons, fixed to no calling, abiding in no place, taking no care of their Families, that under a <hi>pretence of Teaching</hi> the truth without miſſion, without Call, without warrant, uncommanded, undeſired, do go up and down from place to place, creeping into Houſes, &amp;c. Now that ſuch waies as theſe, and perſons in theſe waies may bee <hi>judicially enquired into,</hi> I no way doubt: I did yet never obſerv any other iſſue upon ſuch undertakings, but <hi>ſcandal</hi> to Religion, and <hi>trouble</hi> to men in their <hi>civil Relations;</hi>
               </q> Therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſiles order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.24. Let every man in the ſame Calling wherein hee was Called (to Chriſtianitie) therein abide with God, ſtudying to bee quiet, and to <hi>do his own buſineſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>and not other mens,</hi> as the Lord hath commanded.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> The chief Argument for preaching without Ordination, is taken from <hi>Act.</hi> 8 <hi>ver.</hi> 4. with <hi>Act.</hi> 11.19, 20. they that were ſcattered abroad upon the perſecution that aroſe about <hi>Stephen,</hi> went every where preaching the Word, yet theſe that were ſcattered, were <hi>not Ordained men,</hi> therefore men <hi>unordained</hi> may Preach.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> 1. It muſt bee in ſuch caſes as in the Text, This example will not hold in caſes altogether <hi>unlike:</hi> Suppoſe that when Miniſters are perſecuted, Congregations ſcattered, when Chriſtians are fain to flie into ſtrange Countries among Infidels, when ſuch cannot bee had, as by God's ordinary Call have power to preach, I ſay, admit that in ſuch a Caſe, any man may preach the Word, declare among the people the name of Jeſus Chriſt, his Death and Reſurrection; yet by what <hi>analogie of reaſon</hi> can this bee alleged againſt the <hi>establiſhed courſ</hi> provided in Scripture for ſending men to preach? In Caſe of extreme danger, when I am <hi>aſſaulted for my life,</hi> I may rather kill then bee killed, I may bee my <hi>own Magiſtrate;</hi> But this warrant's not an <hi>ordinarie uſurping of the Magiſtrates ſword;</hi> ſo in our preſent Queſtion:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>
               </label> When wee have a <hi>Rule</hi> and an <hi>extraordinarie</hi> Example that croſſeth that Rule (as in the caſe of <hi>Phinees</hi> and <hi>Abraham's</hi> killing his ſon) then wee muſt <hi>leav the Example and follow the Rule;</hi> wee muſt not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>diſpenſations</hi> and forſake the <hi>ſtanding precept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> 2. But how will it appear that theſe <hi>[They]</hi> in the Text, that <hi>preached abread,</hi> were men <hi>unſent and unordained?</hi> ſeeing there bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts in Scripture for Ordination,<note place="margin">Col. 4.10, 11. Philem. v. 24.</note> if wee finde any <hi>doing</hi> the work of Elders, wee are to <hi>preſume</hi> that they are Ordained, though their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40677:16"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label> bee not <hi>recorded,</hi> as <hi>Marcus Ariſtarchus, Demas, Lucas, Tychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, &amp;c.</hi> And that <hi>thoſe preachers above mentioned,</hi> were <hi>ſo ſent,</hi> I ſhall offer unto you, for proof, theſe <hi>Textual</hi> conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All that are <hi>named,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9.10. Act. 21.8.</note> as <hi>Philip</hi> the Evangeliſt, and <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Lucius</hi> of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> were men in Office.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nothing appear's to the contrarie, but all make's for it, That <hi>the ſeventie were at Jeruſalem</hi> till that ſcattering, they kept companie with Chriſt while hee lived, and <hi>with the Apoſtles</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> after hee was Aſcended, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.21. <hi>(For out of the ſeventie, Matthias</hi> was choſen to bee an Apoſtle,) and becauſ they neſtled themſelvs in their warm quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> God ſend's a perſecution to <hi>diſperſ them about</hi> their buſineſs, that ſo the preaching might bee more fully known ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as Chriſt fore-told, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.8. ſo it came to paſs the <hi>ſeventie were appointed</hi> to preach in the places where <hi>thoſe that were ſcattered, did preach, Act.</hi> 8.1. Therefore it is altogether likely that theſe were the men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Beſides, it is ſaid, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.7. that a great Companie of the <hi>Prieſts were Converted</hi> to the Faith, and theſe were <hi>Paul's Fellow-helpers</hi> unto the Kingdom of God, <hi>Ariſtarchus</hi> and <hi>Marcus,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus</hi> which is called <hi>Juſtus, who are of the Circumciſion,</hi> theſe were <hi>Preachers</hi> of the Goſpel with <hi>Paul, Col.</hi> 4.10, 11. And they beeing <hi>Priests,</hi> were Autorized by their <hi>former Calling</hi> to preach. Therefore when the Text ſaies, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1. They were <hi>all</hi> ſcattered abroad except the Apoſtles, this cannot bee meant of <hi>all the Church</hi> (for there remained many houſholds of them, <hi>verſ</hi> 3.) but of them, who did <hi>preach Chriſt</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> as <hi>Stephen</hi> had don, theſe were eſpecially aimed at in the perſecution, and they <hi>ſeeing</hi> how it fared with <hi>Stephen,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelvs to preach abroad, the Apoſtles that remained behinde were perſecuted, <hi>James</hi> was killed with the ſword, and <hi>Peter</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.2.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Circumſtance evidencing this Truth, is that of <hi>Act.</hi> 11.20. where it is ſaid, that <hi>ſom of them</hi> were men of <hi>Cyrene and Cyprus,</hi> who when they were com to <hi>Antioch,</hi> ſpake unto the <hi>Grecians,</hi> preaching the Lord Jeſus. By theſe, wee may judg <hi>what the reſt of them that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed were,</hi> when 'tis ſaid, <hi>ſom of them</hi> were men of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> the reſt were of the <hi>ſame rank,</hi> though not of the ſame Cities. But theſe men of <hi>Cyrene</hi> and <hi>Cyprus,</hi> were they <hi>lawfully Called</hi> and ſent forth to preach?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Had they <hi>any ſpecial Calling?</hi> I conceiv they had for theſe reaſons:</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40677:16"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, Becauſ they were the <hi>firſt</hi> that converted the people of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> unto the Faith,   <hi>Act.</hi> 11.21, 22, 24. And God <hi>gave testimonie</hi> to their word by ſigns and wonders, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. the hand of the Lord was with them, <hi>viz.</hi> to heal the ſick, &amp;c. as was uſual in the firſt planting of Churches. If they had not an <hi>ordinarie</hi> Calling, yet ſurely they had <hi>an extraordinarie one,</hi> becauſ their Doctrine was <hi>confirmed with ſigns</hi> following, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, Theſe <hi>wonder-working Preachers continued</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi>  
               <note place="margin">Act. 11.22.</note> till <hi>Barnabas</hi> was ſent thither unto them from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to confirm the people in the Faith, theſe men <hi>continuing at Antioch,</hi> are <hi>expreſly called Prophets and Teachers, Act.</hi> 13 1. Now there were in the Church that was at <hi>Antioch</hi> certain Prophets and Teachers, as <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and <hi>Simon</hi> called <hi>Niger,</hi> and <hi>Lucius</hi> of <hi>Cyrene;</hi> and theſe miniſtred unto the Lord, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, They that are called <hi>Prophets and Teachers, Act.</hi> 13.1. are the <hi>verie ſame that fled and came firſt to Antioch</hi> and converted that people, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.19. For 'tis ſaid, <hi>verſ</hi> 20. that they were men of <hi>Cyprus</hi> and <hi>Cyrene that came firſt to Antioch and preached,</hi> and one of them, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1. is <hi>Lucius</hi> of <hi>Cyrene: Lucius</hi> therefore of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> (called a Prophet, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1.) was one of them that fled from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon that Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.20. Hence I gather that ſeeing they that <hi>preached</hi> at <hi>Antioch</hi> and converted them, <hi>were Prophets and Teachers:</hi> And they that converted the <hi>Antiochians</hi> were <hi>the ſame that fled from Jeruſalem</hi> upon that perſecution, therefore they that <hi>fled and preached were not men meerly Gifted,</hi> but duly Called.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Textual</hi> circumſtances give ſufficient ground to affirm that thoſe which preached upon that ſcattering, had ſom ſpiritual Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereunto; far better grounds then can bee alleged to the contrarie. Put altogether thus: They <hi>all, i. e.</hi> they which had kept companie with the Apoſtles and were of the ſeventie, or of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Prieſts, <hi>They are they that preached abroad:</hi> 1. Becauſ they onely are named: 2. Becauſ the ſeventie were appointed to preach in <hi>thoſe places where they that were ſcattered,</hi> did preach: 3. Becauſ they were men approved by ſigns and wonders: 4. Becauſ ſom of them are expreſly Called Prophets and Teachers, beeing the <hi>very ſame men</hi> that came to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and fled from <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Let the ſame bee ſaid of you, and then preach in God's name, elſ ſuch a pattern will not <hi>juſtifie</hi> you, nor bee a fit parallel for for your actions.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40677:17"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Apollos</hi> was <hi>no</hi> ordained Miniſter, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Church-members ſet in joint, by</hi> Filo. dexter Tranſylvanus againſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenden. p. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> yet hee preached, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.24.</p>
            <p>Hee was an <hi>Autorized publick</hi> Preacher in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> for who is <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> but <hi>Ministers</hi> by whom yee believ, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak's of him, as his <hi>fellow-laborer. and ſteward</hi> of the myſteries of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 1, 6. Yea, it ſeem's that <hi>Apollos</hi> did Baptize as well as preach, for the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were divided into Sects according to the <hi>Names and Number</hi> of them that taught, and baptized them, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.) as <hi>Paul's miſliking</hi> of them doe's import, <hi>verſ</hi> 13. were yee baptized into the Name of <hi>Paul?</hi> And ſeeing ſom did call themſelvs by the <hi>name of Apollo,</hi> it follow's <hi>that hee did alſo Baptize from which time</hi> they would call themſelvs by the name of <hi>Apollo</hi> as others did of <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Its true indeed, <hi>Apollos</hi> preached at <hi>Epheſus</hi> before hee came to <hi>Corinth, Act.</hi> 18.24, 27. But ſeeing wee read that hee <hi>was a Minister,</hi> and yet read of <hi>no new Ordination</hi> received after his coming to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> wee muſt conclude, that hee was an autorized Preacher when hee preached at <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But hee knew onely the baptiſm of <hi>John, i. e.</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>John,</hi> hee had been baptized <hi>onely with water in the</hi> name of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> What of that? Yet hee might bee as <hi>true a Miniſter</hi> of the New Teſtament as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> himſelf: for <hi>John</hi> taught the people that they muſt repent and believ on Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo hee baptized them, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.4. The <hi>ſame Doctrine</hi> did <hi>Apollos</hi> preach, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.25, 28. Hee taught diligently the things of the Lord, and mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced the Jews that Jeſus was Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> and of Chriſt <hi>diſtinguiſhed, Act.</hi> 19.4, 5. are <hi>not two Baptiſms of water,</hi> but onely one with water which is called <hi>John's Baptiſm, Act.</hi> 19.3. and the <hi>Lord's Baptiſm, Act.</hi> 8.16. But <hi>Chriſt's Baptiſm in diſtinction from John's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.44, 46.</note> was the <hi>pouring forth</hi> of the holy Ghoſt upon the Apoſtles, and others in thoſe daies, as <hi>S. Peter</hi> doe's <hi>expound it, Act.</hi> 11.15, 16. ſaying, That as I began to ſpeak, the holy Ghoſt fell on them, as on us at the beginning, <hi>then remembred I the words</hi> of the Lord, how hee ſaid, <hi>John indeed</hi> baptized with water, but yee ſhall bee baptized with the holy Ghoſt—compare, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.15, 16. when <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were com to <hi>Samaria,</hi> they praied for them, that they <hi>might receiv the holy Ghoſt,</hi> for as yet hee was fallen upon none of them, <hi>onely they were baptized in the Name</hi> of the Lord Jeſus.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40677:17"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> This Baptiſm of the holy Ghoſt ſhed on them, was <hi>uſually don by the laying on not of water,</hi> but of hands, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.6.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaie's 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. yee may all prophecie one by one, that all may learn, for the miniſtration of the Spirit is given to every one to profit withal, Chap. 12.7. therefore all that bee able, may preach.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s purpoſe there, is to give directions concerning the uſe of ſpiritual gifts, ſpecially that of Tongues and Prophecie; And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſ ſome uſed their gifts for <hi>oſtentation,</hi> not for edification; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee telleth them, that in what kind ſoëver <hi>any gift manifesting the Spirit,</hi> is beſtowed on any man, it is to this <hi>one end,</hi> for the proſit of all, Chap. 12.7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Note that theſe gifts were <hi>diverſly diſtributed,</hi> not given <hi>all to one,</hi> nor <hi>any one gift to all;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12, 10.</note> but to <hi>one</hi> was given to ſpeak with Tongues, to <hi>another</hi> Miracles, to <hi>another</hi> Prophecie. And every one might exerciſe his <hi>own gift, but not anothers:</hi> Hee that had the gift of Miracles, might do his Miracle, but <hi>not go about</hi> to ſpeak with Tongues, and hee that ſpake with <hi>Tongues</hi> might not attempt to heal nor to Prophecie; God gave not all theſe gifts to one, but one to one, another to another,<note place="margin">verſ 11.</note> 
               <hi>dividing in parts</hi> to every man as hee will. Prophecie was a chief gift, extraordinarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, as was the gift of Tongues or healing, and the Prophets <hi>were they,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>which by a ſpecial</hi> and extraordinarie gift interpreted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical Scriptures to edification and conſolation; Now <hi>Paul</hi> beeing to <hi>regulate</hi> this gift, ſaith, yee may all prophecie one by one, <hi>i. e. all that bee Prophets,</hi> all that have a matter revealed to them, <hi>(verſ</hi> 30. if any thing bee revealed to another that ſitteth by, &amp;c.) <hi>All,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12, 29.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch may take their turns in Prophecying, not any one elſ;</hi> for at <hi>Corinth, all</hi> were not Prophets.</p>
            <p>This then 'is the plain meaning of that place, as hee that had not the gift of Tongues or of healing might not attempt to heal or to ſpeak with Tongues, ſo hee that had not the gift of prophecie, might not undertake to exerciſe it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſ our men take theſe Prophets to bee <hi>ordinarie gifted</hi> Chriſtians, and ſo their <hi>practices imitable:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.</note> I ſhall by three reaſons prove the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That prophecying in that place, was an extraordinarie, and not a <hi>ſtanding ordinarie gift</hi> in the Church.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſ <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaie's of them, that they had ſom <hi>ſpecial</hi> matters <hi>revealed to them of a ſudden,</hi> whilſt another was prophecying, they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40677:18"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>3</label>
               <hi>onely ſitting by,</hi> and not <hi>uſing the help or operation</hi> of any facultie of their <hi>own,</hi> as their wit, memorie, reading: they ſpake by divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, like the old Prophets.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. And accordingly wee finde them in a <hi>rank and order</hi> of men ſet with the Apoſtles <hi>above the most</hi> eminent Gifted Chriſtians, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. firſt Apoſtles <hi>ſecondarily Prophets</hi>—And as the Apoſtles, ſo they <hi>had their knowledg</hi> of the myſterie of chriſt <hi>by revelation,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 3.5. as it is now <hi>revealed</hi> to his holy Apoſtles and <hi>Prophets by the Spirit.</hi> Prophecie therefore was no <hi>ſtanding gift,</hi> and Prophets were not ordinarie gifted believers, but a rank of men in Office above Paſtors.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. All theſe gifts (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14) were of the ſame nature for the <hi>manner of their Donation,</hi> and for their <hi>continuance, i. e.</hi> to laſt for a time onely, wherefore ſeeing the gift of <hi>Tongues and Miracles</hi> is ceaſed, the gift of Prophecie is <hi>alſo ceaſed,</hi> for this was given in the ſame manner, and placed among the extraordinarie gifts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. whereupon I conclude, that the <hi>Prophecying</hi> in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> is no <hi>pattern for the practice</hi> of our gifted Speakers, who, I preſume, have not the <hi>face to take the place of Prophets next to the Apoſtles above Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts and Paſtors,</hi>—Nor to affirm that they have their knowledg by <hi>revelation</hi> [for then what need they <hi>plead their parts or gifts,</hi> ſeeing Inſpiration or Revelation is not a facultie of the minde.] and ſeeing the gift or prophecie is <hi>ceaſed,</hi> it is now a groſs <hi>taking of the name to counterfeit it,</hi> as alſo it is to <hi>imitate</hi> the miraculous works of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> If they had been inſpired, they could not bee <hi>ſubject to the judging</hi> of others, ſeeing they could not then err: But the Text ſaies, that the ſpirit of thoſe Prophets is ſubject unto the Prophets; therefore they were but ordinarie men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29.32.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> This Argument follow's not becauſ the Apoſtles <hi>were inſpired</hi> and could not err, yet they ſubmitted their Doctrine to trial, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. And becauſ Satan ean transform himſelf into <hi>an Angel</hi> of Light, and his miniſters as the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1. 1 Joh. 4.1.</note> and becauſ as there were falſ Prophets of old, ſo there ſhall bee <hi>falſ teachers</hi> among you, for <hi>this cauſ</hi> wee are commanded to <hi>trie their ſpirits, ie.</hi> the Doctrines pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded under the name of the <hi>ſpirits inſtiration:</hi> And to prevent <hi>diluſions in this kind,</hi> God gave a gift of diſcerning of ſpirits, whereby to know a true Prophet from a falſ, which ſpake for his own ſpirit: yea, the Prophets themſelvs had a <hi>ſpirit of judging, verſ</hi> 29. And
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40677:18"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> therefore it was ordained that the Doctrine of every Prophet ſhould bee ſubject to the <hi>Examination</hi> of other Prophets, who ought to judg by the <hi>Rule of God's Word,</hi> whether that which was ſpoken, were by the <hi>motion of God's Spirit,</hi> or by a ſpirit <hi>meerly humane;</hi> and this was no <hi>diſparagement</hi> to thoſe Prophets, to have their Doctrine and Interpretations judged by others endued with the <hi>ſame Spirit. (Nam etſi bomo ſpiritualis à nemine judicatur, tamen qui à nemine judicatur, judicatur à ſpiritu Dei.)</hi> Theſe Prophets were <hi>greater then the Ordinarie</hi> Paſtors and Doctors, yet <hi>inferior to the Apoſtles</hi> and Prophets which were the Pen-men of holy Scripture,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lect. Apoer. To.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 34 <hi>p.</hi> 300, 301, 305.</note> as that learned Dr <hi>Rainolds</hi> hath obſerved) they had indeed <hi>gifts and inſpirations more</hi> then ordinarie for opening of Scriptures, but not the Spirit ſo <hi>inceſſantly aſſiſting them,</hi> as they had that <hi>wrote</hi> the Scrptures. <hi>Nathan</hi> though a Prophet, yet hee had not the ſpirit inceſſantly ſpeaking in him, hee ſpake out of his <hi>own humane judgment</hi> and reaſon,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.31.</note> when hee had <hi>David</hi> to build the Temple, ſo did <hi>Samuel</hi> judg concerning <hi>Eliab</hi> the eldeſt ſon of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.6, 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meminiſſe oportet</hi> (ſaith Dr <hi>Rainolds)</hi>) <hi>dona ſpiritûs ſecundùm menſuram hominibus diſtributa eſſe, &amp; cùm inſint in ill is primitiae quidem Spiritûs Sancti, unà etiam ineſſe reliquias ſpiritûs humani. Nemo autem novit, quae ſunt hominis, niſi ſpiritus hominis; Nec quiſpiam novit, quae ſunt Dei, niſi Spiritus Dei; Ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quae tradunt viri Dei, Prophetae hi, de quibus loquimur, profecta eſſe poſſunt ab humano ſpiritu, qui adhue etiam in illis eſt, idcirco do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinam ſuam ſubmittere debem fratrum ſuorum examini &amp; judicio, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim omnia ſemper Deus ſervis ſuis revelat, ſed id quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poteſt aliquando dicere, quòd Elizeus, cùm adipſum Shunamitis accederet, hoc Jehova celavit me, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> indicavit mihi,</hi> ibi. p 305.</p>
            <p>If their Doctrine <hi>may bee judged,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 4 27.</note> it may bee <hi>refuſed as beeing poſſibly</hi> ſubject to error, not <hi>when they ſpeak by Inſpiration,</hi> but becauſ <hi>'tis poſſible,</hi> they might ſpeak by a <hi>humane ſpirit,</hi> or <hi>by a falſ ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>that could not bee known, but by examination;</hi> therefore the Apoſtle will have thoſe Prophets Teaching <hi>ſubmitted</hi> to the judgment of others, that have the ſpirit of Prophecie, that ſo by the <hi>harmonie</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> of their Doctrines, the <hi>unitie</hi> of the ſpirit, by which they all ſpeak,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.37.</note> may bee <hi>evidenced</hi> and approved. Now this could not befal the <hi>Pen-men</hi> of holy Scripture, who ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt, and not of their <hi>own ſpirits</hi> at any time when they preach't or writ any part of Scripture. Whatſoëver the Apoſtles preached or wrote, it is of Divine Autoritie, becauſ they wrote it.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40677:19"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Concluſ. </seg>3</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> Som be ſo inconſiderate as to plead for their pattern and warrant Chriſt's making <hi>Preachers of Fiſhermen;</hi> why therefore may not Tradſmen preach?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Nothing can make more directly againſt you: 1. Chriſt called them <hi>from their Trades</hi> to an higher imploiment to bee Fiſhers of men, and they <hi>left their Trades</hi> to do this Work; But you ſay, <hi>keep on your Trades and preach too.</hi> 2. Chriſt, who is the Autor of the Miniſterie of New Teſtament, <hi>Called them, trained them up</hi> in his School as Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, then hee <hi>Ordained Twelv</hi> that they. ſhould bee with him, that hee might ſend them to preach, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.14. But you preach without any ſuch Calling, Training up, Ordaining or ſending. 3. Chriſt ſent them out two and two to preach, and <hi>gave them power</hi> to heal the ſick, cleanſ the Leapers, raiſ the dead, caſt out Divels. Chriſt <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled</hi> them for the work which hee ſent them about; But you have no <hi>ſuch miſſion,</hi> nor <hi>new abilities:</hi> Here is the difference between Chriſt and men, hee doe's not <hi>finde men fit,</hi> but <hi>make's them fit,</hi> and ſo ſend's them; But wee muſt <hi>finde them</hi> fit, or elſ not ſend them: Neither muſt any run before they bee ſent. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.21. I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ran, &amp;c. Theſe are the chief Arguments for preaching without Ordination, for farther ſatisfaction wherein, and of all M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Chillenden</hi>'s Objections, I refer the Reader to that acute, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid ſhort Treatiſe, entituled, <hi>Church-members ſet in joint,</hi> written by <hi>Filodexter Tranſylvanus;</hi> and I the rather recommend that Treatiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſ my people have grounded their Opinion and Practice upon Mr <hi>Chillenden</hi>'s Book.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40677:19"/>
               <head>The ſecond Queſtion.</head>
               <p>WHether Baptiſm belong's and bee rightly adminiſtred to Infants of Chriſtian Parents in the New Teſtament? Affir?</p>
               <p>Baptiſm is the firſt <hi>viſible Act of God's Grace</hi> whereby hee doth receiv us into his favor and familie: And the <hi>firſt viſible means</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee doth <hi>apply to us</hi> by Word, Sign and Seal the blood of Jeſus Chriſt for remiſſion of ſins. Now the Queſtion is to whom this Seal of mercie doth belong.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have ſundrie pretences to ſcorn and deride Infant bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: in their account the Baptiſm of Infants is no Baptiſm, becauſ according to Chriſt's Inſtitution (as they conceiv) true Baptiſm doth alwaies <hi>preſuppoſe actual belief</hi> in the receivers, and is otherwiſe no Baptiſm; therefore they <hi>rebaptize.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others allow of Infant-baptiſm, they eſteem it as an Ordinance which Chriſt hath inſtituted in ſpecial love and favor to his people, <hi>onely they reſtrain</hi> this priviledg to the Infants of Parents who joyn themſelvs in Church-Covenant to ſom particular Congregation. My debate is with the former, who deny <hi>all Infant-baptiſm,</hi> the which, if it be proved to belong to any Infants, it is enough for my purpoſe; and the <hi>ſame Arguments</hi> which prove it to belong to Infants of <hi>this or that Congregation,</hi> do prove it to belong to the whole viſible Church and their Infants; it being a vain pride and great preſumption to make <hi>new conditions of Church-memberſhip,</hi> which God hath not made, and to aſcribe to the <hi>inventions</hi> of men a power to ſuperſede the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, to caſt both us and our Infants out of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; <hi>us, that were baptized into that one bodie,</hi> if wee ſubſcribe not to their Articles, and our children, becauſ <hi>wee</hi> ſubſcribe not, thus making voide the <hi>Commandment</hi> of god, by the commandments and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of men.</p>
               <p>I the rather force my ſelf to ſpeak ſomthing of this <hi>beaten point,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſ there bee three yong heathens in my Pariſh, and three others
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40677:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>dead out of the Covenant, through their Parents frowardneſs. Now for the convincing and ſatisfying, if it may bee, of theirs, and other poor peoples judgments in the preſent Controverſie, I ſhall content my ſelf with five Arguments; the firſt will depend upon a clear po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Anſwer to another queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Did God make the <hi>Covenant of grace onely with actual Believers, or with them and their Infant-ſeed?</hi> Did God take into Covenant the Parents <hi>with</hi> their children or the Parents <hi>onely?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Not the Parents onely, but with them their Infant-ſeed; this is the expreſs <hi>Tenor of the Covenant, Gen.</hi> 17.7. between God and <hi>Abraham,</hi> between mee and thee, and thy ſeed, to bee a God unto you: <hi>What ſeed</hi> meaneth hee? his <hi>Infant-ſeed, verſ</hi> 12. Hee that is <hi>eight daies old,</hi> whether it bee a child of thy loines, or of a ſtranger, a proſelyte, which is not of thy ſeed: this Covenant was firſt made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gen.</hi> 12.3. wherein God promiſed that in his ſeed ſhall all the Nations of the Earth bee bleſſed,<note place="margin">Of God's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venint.</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> in Chriſt; And it was <hi>renewed with the Sign</hi> of Circumciſion <hi>added</hi> unto it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17 7, 12.</p>
               <p>Wherein obſerv three things:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. That the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham</hi> was the <hi>Goſpel-Covenant,</hi> wherein bleſſedneſs was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in and through Chriſt the promiſed Seed, for God <hi>preached the Goſpel</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> when hee ſaid, In thy ſeed ſhall all Nations bee bleſſed, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoneth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. the which Covenant, ſeeing it was 430 years before the Law, and not diſanulled by the coming of the Law, it was to endure till the Seed ſhould com to whom the promiſs was made, <hi>verſ</hi> 17.19. and <hi>conſequently to the end of the World,</hi> becauſ Chriſt came to eſtabliſh the Covenant made to the Fathers,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.8.</note> and after Chriſt, no more changes to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Note, that the <hi>Perſons with whom</hi> that Goſpel-Covenant was made, were <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Infant-ſeed, and <hi>all Nations, even us Engliſhmen and our Infant-ſeed,</hi> as appear's, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4.12. My Covenant is with thee and with thy ſeed in their Generations, and <hi>with the ſtranger</hi> that is not thy ſeed, all of them muſt bee Circumciſed. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8, 15. Now I ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt was a Miniſter of the <hi>Circumciſion, i. e.</hi> of the Jews, for the truth of God, to <hi>confirm the promiſes</hi> (of the Covenant) made unto the Fathers, and that the <hi>Gentiles might glorifie</hi> God for his mercie, beeing made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with them of the ſame promiſes, according as it is written, Rejoice yee Gentiles with his People, &amp;c. Now <hi>this Covenant</hi> of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40677:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>promiſes made with the Fathers, Chriſt <hi>ſhould not confirm,</hi> but <hi>clip and curtail it,</hi> if ſo great a part as all our Infants bee left out and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded: But if God take our Infants into Covenant, who ſhall dare to exclude them?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Note, when God at <hi>firſt gave</hi> that Covenant to <hi>Abraham</hi> and to the Nations, hee gave withal a <hi>Commandment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 17.12</note> that the <hi>initial</hi> mark of the Covenant ſhould bee ſet upon <hi>all</hi> whom hee had taken into Covenant both Jews and <hi>Gentiles and their Infants:</hi> The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelf and the mark of the Covenant are alike extended to <hi>all the ſame perſons</hi> whether yong or old: Note farther, that when Chriſt, <hi>renewed</hi> and eſtabliſhed that Covenant in his own blood, <hi>though hee changed the Sign,</hi> yet hee <hi>repealed not</hi> that Commandment: Nay,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> hee added a <hi>new commandment,</hi> enjoining the new Sign, Baptiſm, to bee given to all Nations, <hi>without exception</hi> of any perſons <hi>formerly received</hi> into Covenant: ſo that wee are under a <hi>twofold Commandment</hi> to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize our Infants, one, of God who <hi>firſt made</hi> the Covenant and gave that Commandment, the which is ſtill <hi>ſo of force,</hi> that if Chriſt the Lord of the houſ had not changed it, wee were all bound at this day to bee <hi>Circumciſed;</hi> and ſeeing hee hath <hi>changed that Sign into Baptiſm,</hi> but not the Covenant it ſelf, nor the <hi>Commandment</hi> thereto annexed; it followeth, that by the <hi>old Commandment</hi> enjoining Infants to bee marked, and by Chriſt's <hi>new Commandment,</hi> enjoining <hi>Baptiſm</hi> to bee <hi>that mark; all, that are not excepted</hi> out of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſtand bound to recei it. In like manner as the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment injoining one day of ſeven for an holy Reſt to the Lord, doth binde <hi>us</hi> to obſerv <hi>our Lords-day;</hi> the Commandment ſtand's of force, <hi>though the firſt day</hi> bee changed: ſo the Commandment for <hi>ſigning of the Nations</hi> whom God received into Covenant <hi>and their ſeed,</hi> doth ſtill oblige us to <hi>ſet the New Seal</hi> upon them; eſpecially, ſeeing wee are again commanded by Chriſt ſo to do without any exception of Infants. Hence I thus argue,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>1</label> All that are taken into the Covenant of Grace, ought to receiv the judicial Sign of the Covenant [what ever the Sign be, that God ſhall chuſe,] and that according to the Commandment of God and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But Infants are taken into Covenant with their Parents, as is proved; therefore <hi>by the Commandment</hi> of the Lord, they <hi>ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cev the Sign</hi> which God hath enjoined to bee uſed, and that Sign is Baptiſm:</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:40677:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Or thus,</p>
               <p>If Infants have a <hi>right</hi> to the Covenant and the <hi>initial ſign thereof</hi> then it is a <hi>wrong to deny them.</hi> But Infants have a right to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and the initial Sign thereof both by God's <hi>Original Grant. Gen.</hi> 17.11, 14. And by <hi>Chriſt's confirmation</hi> of that Covenant made with the Fathers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8. therefore it is a wrong to deny it to them. The Covenant under which wee are <hi>is the Goſpel-Covenant,</hi> made long ſince with <hi>us Engliſhmen and our Infant-ſeed,</hi> with a <hi>command of giving them the Sign,</hi> which at firſt was Circumciſion, and now Baptiſm by the <hi>ſame Divine Autoritie enjoyned,</hi> and commanded to bee given without any exception of any within the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument </seg>2</label> My ſecond Argument is grounded on <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38, 39. then <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, Repent and bee baptized, &amp;c. In which paſſage of Scripture, I note three things.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Who the <hi>perſons were,</hi> of whom <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, The promiſe is to you and to your children, they were a mixt multitude of <hi>many Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> as appears, <hi>verſ</hi> 10. <hi>ſtrangers of Rome,</hi> Jews, <hi>Proſelyts, Creets, and Arabians.</hi> Note</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>What promiſe that is,</hi> of which S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaies, <hi>it belongs to ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and their children,</hi> and is applied to his hearers <hi>as the ground</hi> of their beeing baptized: It is that <hi>grand promiſe</hi> made to <hi>Abraham</hi> to bee a God to him and his ſeed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that Goſpel-promiſs of good tidings, <hi>gratuitum Dei promiſſum, quatenùs opponitur legi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beza;</hi> in a word, it is that promiſs of <hi>bleſſedneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 31.34.</note> which conſiſts in <hi>remiſſion of ſins</hi> to bee obtained by the promiſed Meſſiah.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Nay, Why not rather underſtand it of the promiſe of the <hi>gifts of the holy Ghoſt</hi> promiſed <hi>Joel</hi> 2.27. <hi>and given by laying on of the Apoſtles hands,</hi> eſpecially becauſ it is ſaid in the end of <hi>verſ</hi> 38. Bee baptized and yee ſhall receiv the gift of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> The <hi>promiſe here ſpoken of,</hi> cannot bee underſtood (I conceiv) of the miraculous gifts of the holie Ghoſt. 1. Becauſ <hi>Peter's bearers received no ſuch gifts,</hi> and therefore S. <hi>Peter</hi> made <hi>no ſuch promiſe</hi> to them, for doubtleſs they received what was promiſed. 2. <hi>Such</hi> a promiſe muſt here bee underſtood as belongs to <hi>Parents and their children, and to all that ſhall bee called to the worlds end;</hi> But there is no ſuch promiſe in all the Scripture, that the <hi>miraculous gifts</hi> of the holie Ghoſt ſhall fall upon Parents with their children, and <hi>all that are</hi> to bee converted to the worlds end. 3. A promiſe of ſuch gifts ſeems not <hi>ſutably applied</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:40677:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>to <hi>Peter</hi>'s hearers comfort; for their Queſtion was, what ſhall wee do to bee <hi>ſaved?</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> gives them; 1. A direction: 2. And a Promiſe: A direction to <hi>repent,</hi> and to <hi>acknowledg</hi> Chriſt to bee head and foundation of the Covenant of Grace, and that life and remiſſion of ſins is in <hi>his blood,</hi> where of Baptiſm is the Seal: And then hee <hi>recites and applies</hi> to this comfort the promiſes of the Covenant, <hi>q. d.</hi> yee ſhall receiv the benefit of the Covenant, <hi>remiſſion of ſins,</hi> and alſo <hi>the gift of the holie Spirit,</hi> the Seal thereof; thoſe <hi>firſt motions</hi> now begun in your hearts, ſhall bee followed with increaſ of Sanctification of ſpiritual light, of joy, comfort and aſſurance. This interpretation doth exactly agree with the Apoſtles <hi>diſcourſ, Gal.</hi> 3.14. where ſpeaking of the <hi>bleſsing of Abraham</hi> to com on the Gentiles, hee ſaith, that wee being delivered from the Curſe, and reſtored into God's Grace by Chriſt, ſhall <hi>receiv the promiſe of the Spirit</hi> through Faith, <hi>i.e.</hi> the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of Grace (which is the Seal of the promiſes of the new Covenant) <hi>the gifts of the holie Spirit</hi> which had been <hi>ſo often, and ſo ſolemnly</hi> promiſed by the Prophets, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 44.3. I will pour water upon him that is <hi>thirſtie</hi> (as <hi>Peters hearers now were)</hi> and Floods upon the drie ground, I will pour my <hi>ſpirit upon thy ſeed,</hi> and my bleſſing upon thine off-ſpring, and one ſay, I am the Lords, and another ſhall call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by the name of <hi>Jacob,</hi> with <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19. &amp; cap. 36.27. <hi>A new ſpirit</hi> will I put within you, I will take the ſtonie heart out of your fleſh, and give you an heart of fleſh:<note place="margin">Act. 2.38. Gal. 3.2, 14.</note> So that the <hi>gift of the Spirit</hi> in <hi>Peter's</hi> Sermon, and the <hi>promiſe of the ſpirit</hi> in the <hi>Galatians</hi> and in <hi>the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> is all one thing for ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>As for that place <hi>Joel</hi> 2.27. S. <hi>Peter</hi> expounds it, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17. of the <hi>deſcending</hi> of the holy Ghoſt upon the Apoſtles in fierie Tongues, and it may well have <hi>relation</hi> to all thoſe, upon whom in <hi>like manner it did deſcend:</hi> But if any man conceivs, that that place hath a farther <hi>accompliſhment</hi> in the New Teſtament in the <hi>larger</hi> pouring forth of the gifts of the ſpirit of <hi>illumination</hi> and underſtanding in the <hi>mysteries of Chriſt,</hi> and his Kingdom <hi>more generally</hi> upon all ſorts and conditions of people, and in a <hi>greater meaſure,</hi> ſo that <hi>all ſorts and ſexes, now, ſhall have as much,</hi> or more light and illumination then the Prophets had in the old Teſtament; the <hi>common light</hi> of the Elect now under the Goſpel ſhall bee <hi>clearer and better,</hi> then that of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of old, (according to that of <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.8. Hee that is <hi>feeble, ſhall bee as David</hi> and the houſ of <hi>David,</hi> as the Angel of the Lord.) I ſhall not withſtand him, and ſo that place of <hi>Joel</hi> in this large ſenſ,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40677:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>doth contain a part of the promiſes of the new Covenant, whereof Baptiſm is a Seal. But as for thoſe <hi>miraculous gifts</hi> of the holie Ghoſt, I no where finde them <hi>communicated with or annexed unto Baptiſm.</hi> Sometimes they were poured forth <hi>before Baptiſm</hi> received at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's preaching, as upon <hi>Peter's</hi> hearers that were with <hi>Cornelius, Act.</hi> 10.45, 47. Somtimes <hi>after Baptiſm,</hi> by another Ceremonie of laying on of hands, as <hi>Act.</hi> 8.16, 17. <hi>Act.</hi> 19.6.—Somtimes upon <hi>their fervent praiers,</hi> as <hi>Act.</hi> 4.31. And upon theſe conſiderations it is, that I take the promiſs here ſpoken of and applied to <hi>Peter's</hi> hearers and their children, to bee the promiſe of <hi>bleſſedneſs made</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> and all Converts.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third thing to bee obſerved in <hi>Peter</hi>'s words, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. is this that this promiſe, (bee it what it will) did belong <hi>as well to his hearers children, as to themſelvs,</hi> (it is to you and your children.)</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> True ſay they, when they are in a <hi>capacitie to receiv</hi> the promiſs, <hi>i.e.</hi> to as many of our children as are <hi>calld to actual faith,</hi> not of our Infants.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> This is a miſerable ſhift for thoſe words, <hi>[as many as the Lord our God ſhall call]</hi> are quite a <hi>new thing,</hi> clearly <hi>relating to another ſort of people,</hi> then his preſent hearers, <hi>viz. All that are afar off,</hi> which as yet never heard of Chriſt. Thoſe words do not <hi>exegetically</hi> expound <hi>to which of his hearers children</hi> the promiſs did belong, as if <hi>Peter</hi> meant to tell them, <hi>to ſom of their children</hi> it doe's belong not to others, but by the very order of the Text, they <hi>point out others</hi> that were afar off, in their <hi>ſeveral generations</hi> to bee called by the Goſpel, to whom ſaie's <hi>Peter</hi> this promiſe doe's belong, to them and their children, <hi>as well as to you,</hi> and your children. The <hi>children</hi> then of <hi>Peter's Converts</hi> were within the promiſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Obſerv <hi>Peter's reaſoning and argumentatisn,</hi> in this word [For] <hi>verſ</hi> 39. where S. <hi>Peter</hi> give's <hi>a reaſon of his direction,</hi> why thoſe hearers ſhould bee baptized, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſ that <hi>grand promiſs of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> by remiſſion of ſins, did belong to them; and upon this, as upon a <hi>principal foundation,</hi> he build's his Exhortation to them to bee bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; the holy Ghoſt in that <hi>manner of reaſoning</hi> clearly <hi>teaching this Doctrine.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> viz. <hi>To as many as the bleſſings or promiſs of the Covenant belong's, to them alſo belong's Baptiſm;</hi> For <hi>therefore doe's the Sign belong to</hi> Peter's <hi>hearers,</hi> becauſ the Promiſs did <hi>firſt belong to them.</hi> And by the <hi>like reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the ſame Apoſtle doth <hi>juſtifie his Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Family, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.47, 48. Can any forbid water that theſe ſhould not bee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40677:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>baptized who have received the holie Ghoſt as well as wee? And hee commanded them to bee baptized in the name of the Lord; which diſcourſ, if <hi>reduced</hi> to form of Argument, ſaie's this; they that <hi>receiv the ſame Grace</hi> are capable of, yea have <hi>right to, the ſame Sign;</hi> but Infants are capable of the ſame Grace (of the holy Ghoſt, and of remiſſion of ſins, as ſhall bee proved anon) therefore <hi>of right they are to receiv the ſame Sign, i.e.</hi> the Sacrament of Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Doctrine</hi> doth our Saviour teach, <hi>uſing the ſame manner of reaſoning;</hi> for the admiſſion of Infants to the outward ſign of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.13, 14. There were that brought unto him little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that hee ſhould put his hands on them and pray; and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>rebuked</hi> them, but Jeſus ſaid, Suffer little children to com unto mee, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God: In which words obſerv 1. <hi>Christ's practice:</hi> 2. <hi>The reaſon of his Practice:</hi> By his practice, <hi>Hee admitted Infants</hi> to the <hi>outward ſign of Bleſſing, though they underſtood not what was ſaid or don unto them,</hi> yet did Chriſt give them his Bleſſing, and the <hi>Sign</hi> thereof (hee laid his hands on them) contrarie to the carnal judgment of his Diſciples, who thought it a <hi>mockerie</hi> to give <hi>Infants a Sign, which they underſtood not.</hi> 2. The <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Chriſt's practice is this, Infants are <hi>not excluded</hi> from the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, therefore they <hi>are not to bee excluded</hi> from the outward Sign of the right and entrie to ſuch a Grace. And if Chriſt did <hi>eſteem it a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon,</hi> why little children ſhould bee admitted to the Sign of his Bleſſing, <hi>becauſ of ſuch is the Kingdom of God;</hi> then by <hi>the ſame reaſon,</hi> Infants muſt bee admitted to Baptiſm and not debarred from the firſt Sign of entrie into Chriſt's Kingdom, <hi>viz. Becauſ the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven</hi> belong's to Infants before actual Faith.</p>
               <p>Now if they will give us leav to make uſe of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's <hi>manner of reaſoning,</hi> my ſecond Argument for Infant Baptiſm will bee this.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>2</label> All thoſe to whom the <hi>Bleſſings and Promiſes</hi> of the Covenant do belong, to them alſo belong's Baptiſm, <hi>the Sign thereof</hi> (by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of St <hi>Peter</hi> and of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.)</p>
               <p>But to <hi>Infams</hi> of believing Parents, the Bleſſings and Promiſs of the Covenant do belong, <hi>before actual Faith;</hi> therefore by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the holie Ghoſt in Scripture, ſuch Infants ought to bee baptized before actual Faith.</p>
               <p>The Major, or firſt part of this Argument, is the very reaſon of the Text: The <hi>Minor Propoſition, viz.</hi> that the Bleſſings and Promiſſes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40677:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Covenant do belong to <hi>Infants before actual Faith,</hi> is proved by theſe reaſons. 1. By the <hi>expreſs words</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> which ſay, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is to your children. 2. By the <hi>expreſs words</hi> of our Saviour, (of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven) 3. By <hi>example</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> they were children of the Promiſe <hi>before actual faith,</hi> and had applied unto them the Seal of the righteouſneſs of Faith. 4. <hi>Som Infants dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are ſaved,</hi> they are members of Chriſt's Kingdom; therefore the <hi>Bleſsing of the Covenant, viz.</hi> Regeneration and Remiſſion of ſins through the blood of Chriſt, do alſo belong to them, for except an <hi>Infant bee born again,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 35.</note> and cleanſed by the bloud of Chriſt, hee cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven;<note place="margin">Heb. 9.22, 23.</note> But <hi>ſom Infants do enter</hi> into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; therefore <hi>ſom Infants</hi> are born again juſtified and ſanctified in the bloud of Chriſt. Now what hath the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> to except againſt this plain Doctrine of Scripture?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> The Bleſſings of the Covenant belong to <hi>Elect</hi> Infants, not to all: Shall wee under that pretence baptize all in general? (This was objected to mee in our Conference.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> If Baptiſm belong but <hi>to one</hi> Infant, it is <hi>enough to confute them</hi> who deny it <hi>to all, becauſ</hi> they are Infants. 2. And if it belong to ſom Infants, why not to all? for who ſhall judg which are elected and which are not? It concerns not us to know who are and who are not Elected, becauſ the <hi>Sacraments do belong</hi> to the Elect, <hi>not as Elect,</hi> but as <hi>viſible members</hi> and Profeſſors; upon which account S. <hi>Peter</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized <hi>Simon Magus:</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> by God's appointment circumciſed <hi>Iſmaël</hi> though a <hi>reprobate, Eſau</hi> and all the children of the fleſh were circumciſed. 3. Laſtly, by your reaſon, Men of years ſhould not bee baptized, becauſ wee cannot tell whether they bee Elected, or not.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> But where have you any <hi>Example</hi> of children baptized?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> There is no <hi>need</hi> of example when wee have the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the holie Ghoſt for it, which is of <hi>greater Autoritie</hi> and force, then bare Example; Howbeit, the practiſe of the Apoſtles may go for an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; their baptizing of whole <hi>houſholds,</hi> is an Example of baptizing <hi>all within the houſ</hi> old and yong, that are not excepted; Even as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s houſhold, are comprehended his Infants: <hi>Abraham</hi> and his houſhold were circumciſed, ſo the Jailor and his houſhold were baptized, the phraſe is the ſame, the caſe the ſame, and why not the perſons?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> Yea, but the Scripture ſaies, <hi>Go, Teach and Baptize:</hi> and they that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40677:23"/>
                  <hi>gladly received</hi> the Word, were baptized: and again they were baptized confeſſing their ſins; therefore men muſt bee <hi>capable of teaching</hi> of Faith and repentance before they bee baptized.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Tis true, When wee <hi>first bring</hi> the Goſpel to a People, they muſt <hi>bee firſt Taught,</hi> confeſs their Faith and their Repentance, and then bee baptized; <hi>But it as true, that when the Parents</hi> have received the Faith and are baptized, their children alſo are taken into Covenant. Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>firſt taught,</hi> and then circumciſed; But his Infants were firſt circumciſed and then taught. This one Error doth much bemiſt your underſtandings, you conceiv that the Covenant take's in <hi>onely actual Believers:</hi> That is indeed a part of the Covenant, but not the <hi>whole extent</hi> of it, as hath been proved. For as wee by <hi>deeds</hi> do <hi>purchaſe and convey Lands</hi> holden in Leaſ or Copie to our children, yea, to children which ſhall bee born, as well as to them that bee already born; and though <hi>our children at that age</hi> knew not what their Fathers did for them, yet when they come to age, they <hi>claim thoſe Lands</hi> by virtue of the Land-Lord's Grant and Seal annexed, paying their Rents and doing their covenanted Services and Homage: So doth the <hi>great Land-Lord</hi> of Heaven put both us and our children into the <hi>Copie of Heaven, and confirms it by Seal of Baptiſm;</hi> And when our children com to have Faith, they may <hi>claim</hi> the good things cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted by <hi>virtue</hi> of God's Grant and Covenant made with their Fathers, they <hi>performing the conditions</hi> of their Father's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p>From Scripture I proceed to ſom <hi>Reaſons</hi> for Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>1</label> Infants are <hi>capable of the thing ſignified</hi> in Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> of the blood of ſprinkling; therefore of Baptiſm it ſelf: If they have the thing ſigned which is <hi>the greater,</hi> why ſhould they bee debarred the <hi>Sign which is the leſs?</hi> It cannot bee denied them upon any juſt ground of Faith or Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Yes, Say they, becauſ Infants have not Faith nor Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> You muſt add 1. that have not Faith, <hi>nor ever will com</hi> to have Faith. 2. You muſt add that they have not Faith <hi>nor any other means of applying Chriſt's blood,</hi> elſ your exception is not ſufficient: In men of years, it is applied by the Spirit of God, and by Faith in Infants by the <hi>Spirit alone,</hi> which is given unto them. It is the <hi>Application of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40677:24"/>Chriſt's righteouſneſs</hi> that juſtifieth us, not <hi>our Act of</hi> apprehending it; the <hi>thing applied, not our Act of applying:</hi> God by his Spirit in Infants doth <hi>all things on our part,</hi> which Faith ſhould do. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. the wind bloweth where it liſteth, thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but canſt not tell whence it cometh and whither it goeth; ſo is everie one that is born after the ſpirit, <hi>i. e.</hi> As the power of God is ſeen in the wind moving the aër, ſo it is in the changing and renewing of us, though the <hi>manner bee bid</hi> from us. Thou knoweſt not what is the way of the Spirit, nor how the bones do grow in the womb of her that is with child, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.5. Thus much wee know from Chriſt's own mouth, that <hi>Infants are bleſſed, for hee bleſſed them, Mar.</hi> 10.16. Shall wee denie it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſ wee know not the <hi>manner how</hi> they are bleſſed? Or, ſhall wee deny them to bee reaſonable creatures, becauſ wee cannot diſcern in them the uſe of reaſon? Or, ſhall wee deny them to bee <hi>ſinners,</hi> becauſ they know not <hi>what the Law is,</hi> nor what the tranſgreſſion of the Law is? Wee need not trouble our ſelvs about the <hi>manner</hi> how Chriſt's righteouſneſs is applied to them, ſeeing God is as gracious to apply unto them the <hi>righteouſneſs of the ſecond Adam,</hi> as in <hi>juſtice</hi> hee did the <hi>ſin and condemnation</hi> of the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That Exception about Faith and Repentance is no more a <hi>barr</hi> againſt the Baptiſm of Infants, then againſt the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of Infants, foraſmuch as in Circumciſion were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <hi>all the ſame qualifications,</hi> which you ſay are required to Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> the inward Circumciſion of the heart.</p>
               <p>Little children muſt bee brought unto Chriſt and none forbid them, and by Baptiſm they <hi>do com unto him,</hi> where the <hi>Miniſter in Chriſt's ſtead receiveth them,</hi> and bleſſeth them, and the Lord ſealeth up unto them their receiving into his favor and grace for his <hi>own mercies</hi> ſake without any merit of ours.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Chriſt <hi>confirmed</hi> the Covenant made unto the Fathers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8. Hee bettered it and no way worſted it: And when hee comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a new Seal to bee ſet in ſtead of Circumciſion, hee did it without altering the ſubſtance of the Covenant in the leaſt degree; but now the <hi>very ſubſtance</hi> of the Covenant would bee <hi>altered to the worſ,</hi> if <hi>ſom perſons formerly</hi> received into Grace, ſhould by Chriſt bee excluded; yea, and Believers children are in <hi>worſ condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40677:24"/>then in the Jewiſh Church, which to affirm, were not onely <hi>derogatorie</hi> to Chriſt's Grace, but againſt Scripture it ſelf, which ſaith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.6. that the Gentiles are <hi>Fellow-heirs with the Jews,</hi> and of the <hi>ſame bodie,</hi> and partakers of his Promiſe in the Goſpel; of which they are not partakers, <hi>nor Fellow-heirs, if ſo great a part of the Gentiles</hi> as their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould bee excluded. The <hi>Infants</hi> of Jews and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyts at the coming of Chriſt had <hi>intereſt</hi> and right to the Covenant of Grace: And if that <hi>right bee taken away,</hi> then their condition after Chriſt is worſ then before: Shall they bee <hi>looſers</hi> by becoming Chriſtians? This, no ſober man will affirm: Neither is this a <hi>complaining</hi> againſt God but againſt them, who would exclude, whom the Lord hath not excluded: God's grace is not <hi>ſtraitned</hi> by Chriſt's coming; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Infants are not excluded.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Our laſt Reaſon is grounded on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſile there ſpeaks <hi>of ſuch an Holineſs,</hi> which belongs to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> children from <hi>this ground,</hi> that one of the Parents is a Believer, and <hi>whereof</hi> the children of Parents beeing both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers <hi>are not capable,</hi> but remain unclean: Now this cannot bee meant of a <hi>civil holineſs</hi> or cleaneſs, for ſo the children of unbelieving Parents were holie, as well as the children of Believers, ſeeing <hi>holie Matrimonie</hi> is not an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance peculiar to the Church: And no where in Scripture are children called <hi>holie,</hi> becauſ their Parents are joined in <hi>holie Wedlock,</hi> and may lawfully live together:<note place="margin">Federal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs what?</note> But it is meant of a <hi>Federal holineſs,</hi> whereby the <hi>children are joyned</hi> with God in Covenant, <hi>dedicated</hi> to his Service, have right to the means of ſalvation, and the ſacrament of Baptiſm, and whereby they are <hi>diſtinguiſhed from Heathens,</hi> Turks,<note place="margin">Apollonius, <hi>p. 84.</hi>
                  </note> and ſuch other Infidels. This <hi>Federal holineſs</hi> is <hi>transferred</hi> from the Parents to the children, not by Generation or Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, but by the <hi>merciful will</hi> of God, whereby hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to bee a God to them and their Seed. Thus the whole Church both yong and old by virtue of God's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with them, are <hi>ſevered from other</hi> Nations, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to God's pure Worſhip and Service, and for <hi>that cauſ are counted holie, Deut.</hi> 14.1, 2. Thou art an <hi>holie people</hi> unto
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40677:25"/>the Lord, with <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.2. the <hi>holy Seed</hi> had mingled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs with the people of thoſe Lands: the <hi>Jews were the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Seed,</hi> the Heathens <hi>unholy,</hi> not becauſ they were illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, or <hi>wanted a civil holineſs,</hi> but becauſ they were without God's Covenant, as <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribeth the <hi>State of all Heathens, Epheſ.</hi> 2.11. Remember that in time paſſed, yee were Gentiles in the fleſh, without Chriſt, Aliens from the Commmon-wealth of <hi>Iſraël, and ſtrangers from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Promiſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Som at <hi>Corinth</hi> thought themſelvs <hi>defiled</hi> by their marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages with Infidels, though contracted <hi>before their converſion,</hi> and thereupon moved a queſtion, Whether it were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to continue their marriage with the unbelieving par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or whether they muſt not ſeek a <hi>ſeparation?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1, 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> is utterly againſt ſeparation, <hi>verſ</hi> 12.13. Let not him <hi>put her away,</hi> and let not the Wife leav her Husband: <hi>His reaſon is, verſ.</hi> 14. Becauſ the unbelieving Wife is ſanctified by the believing Husband, though the <hi>unbelieving partie</hi> bee unclean before God, and is not made an <hi>holy Perſon,</hi> yet the <hi>uſe</hi> of Matrimonie with her is <hi>Holy</hi> to the believing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and of this truth, the holineſs of their children is brought for an <hi>evidence,</hi> to this ſenſ, that <hi>ſeeing the Lord counted their children holy</hi> and in Covenant with him, the believing partie might <hi>reſt aſſured, that their abode</hi> together, and the <hi>uſe</hi> of their marriage is not polluted, but acceptable in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> The ſanctification of the Wife is but a <hi>civil ſanctification</hi> in that place, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſhee is ſanctified to his uſe, that hee ought not to put her away. Again, the holineſs there ſpoken of, is a <hi>fruit of that ſanctification of the Wife,</hi> whereof it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, That ſeeing the effect cannot bee <hi>greater then the Cauſ,</hi> the Cauſ cannot produce a <hi>greater effect then it ſelf,</hi> the Cauſ beeing <hi>onely a civil ſanctification,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, <hi>p.</hi> 166.</note> the holineſs of the children muſt bee the <hi>ſame,</hi> thus argueth <hi>Tho: Collier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. The queſtion was, Whether the Believer were polluted by his unbelieving Wife; the Apoſtle ſaie's, No, <hi>quia pluris eſt pietas unius ad ſanctificandum conjugium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calvin. in loc.</note> 
                  <hi>quàm alterius im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietas
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40677:25"/>ad inquinandum, i. e.</hi> the faith of the Believer is of <hi>greater force to ſanctifie</hi> their preſent cohabitation, then the <hi>unbelief of the other to pollute it.</hi> This hee proveth <hi>from a greater effect and fruit of the Husband's faith,</hi> viz. The <hi>holineſs of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> born of ſuch a Husband by ſuch a woman. The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are holy, not onely <hi>civilly,</hi> as beeing born of <hi>lawful Wedlock,</hi> but <hi>federally as beeing ſevered</hi> from all children of unbelievers by ſpecial prerogative, holy to the Lord, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated unto him, whereas by nature they were Aliens and unclean; according to that of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 11.16. if the root bee holy, ſo are the branches.</p>
               <p>The faith of the believing partie ſanctifieth the unbelieving Wife to bear not onely a <hi>lawful, but an holy Seed; yea,</hi> it ſanctifie's the children and <hi>ſevereth</hi> them from the common condition of other children, which are prophane and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, without the Church, without God in the World.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Note, That <hi>the Holineſs of the child received from one of the Parents believing,</hi> is, <hi>more then the ſanctification of the Wife by her believing Huſband,</hi> becauſ <hi>ſuch a Wife</hi> is not taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Covenant with her husband, but the child is; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaie's not, that <hi>ſuch as is the ſanctification of the Wife;</hi> ſuch is the holineſs of the child: But thus, Such as is the <hi>holineſs of the believing partie,</hi> ſuch is the <hi>childs ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> in reſpect of Church-memberſhip; and ſo the faith of the believing Husband is the <hi>cauſ of both theſe effects,</hi> viz. That <hi>his coupling</hi> with his Wife is not impure, and <hi>alſo that his children are holy:</hi> And this latter <hi>an evidence</hi> of the former. And thus the holineſs of the childe is a <hi>ſign of the mother's</hi> ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification to holy cohabitation, and <hi>an effect of the Father</hi>'s Faith by virtue of God's Covenant. To have ſaid, That their children were <hi>lawful,</hi> was no more then to have ſaid, That their marriage was lawful, which was not the queſtion; But to ſay, that the children of their <hi>lawful</hi> marriage were <hi>holy,</hi> This did inferr not onely the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of their marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age but the <hi>ſanctified</hi> Uſe: As M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Baily</hi> hath well obſerved, of <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> p. 138.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, If by <hi>holy,</hi> bee onely meant <hi>a civil holineſs,</hi> then on the contrarie, by <hi>unclean,</hi> muſt bee meant a <hi>civil uncleanneſs.</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40677:26"/>But when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaie's <hi>(elſ were your children unclean)</hi> his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is not to make them all as an <hi>unclean birth and impure off-ſpring,</hi> which were born at <hi>Corinth</hi> of <hi>unbelieving Parents;</hi> but to ſhew that they are not comprehended within God's Covenant: And ſo when hee ſaie's, <hi>(but now are they holie,)</hi> hee notes ſom <hi>preheminence</hi> of the children of Chriſtians above the <hi>Heathens children:</hi> Though in <hi>civil reſpects,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a lawful birth, both ſorts of children were <hi>equal,</hi> yet that <hi>civil holineſs beeing common to both,</hi> there is a <hi>prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of the Chriſtians child</hi> above the Heathens. The child of an Infidel at <hi>Corinth</hi> is to day <hi>unclean</hi> and the next day <hi>holie,</hi> in caſe his Parents turn <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> And what's the reaſon of this ſo <hi>ſudden alteration?</hi> It muſt needs bee in regard of the <hi>Covenant</hi> into which the partie now believing is taken with his children, his <hi>unbelieving Neighbor</hi> with his children ſtill remaining unclean: Hence I conclude with <hi>Calv. in loc.</hi> Seeing our children are <hi>exempted from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon condition</hi> of loſt mankind, and admitted into God's Church and Family, <hi>Cur eos à ſigno arceamus?</hi> upon what reaſon can wee <hi>drive</hi> them from the <hi>ſign of their admittance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is (ſaith a Learned man) God's great Work to <hi>Church</hi> the World,<note place="margin">A Treatiſe entituled a blow at the root<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> or a diſcoverie of Satan's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, <hi>p.</hi> 154.</note> and the Divel's counter-work is, to <hi>Heathenize the Church.</hi> It troubles the Divel much, that <hi>children</hi> from their infancie ſhould bee under an <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to receiv nurture and admonition in the Lord, to frequent the <hi>Ordinances</hi> and to <hi>own</hi> Jeſus Chriſt by an external pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, if hee could but contriv to <hi>prevent their coming into</hi> that Engagement, hee might hope more eaſily to <hi>keep</hi> them out when they are grown up, then to <hi>work them out,</hi> (ſo grown up) to a <hi>renouncing</hi> of Chriſtianitie, which yet hee hath brought <hi>ſom</hi> unto.</q>
               </p>
               <p>For a cloſe of <hi>both the queſtions hitherto debated,</hi> I deſire to bee reſolved by our Adverſaries, What is <hi>meant by the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of Baptiſm, and <hi>laying on of hands,</hi> reckoned up among the principles of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. By <hi>laying on of Hands,</hi> muſt bee underſtood, <hi>either the rite</hi> of confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſtood 1. In <hi>inſtruction</hi> and examination of thoſe who had been baptized Infants. 2. And in <hi>Praying</hi> for them,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40677:26"/>that God would continue them in the Faith, &amp;c. This was performed, when they grew up to years of diſcretion, and were <hi>called to give account</hi> of their Faith before their admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Lord's Supper. And of this minde is judicious M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Calvin:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſt. l. <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> de confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, <hi>§. 4.</hi>
                  </note> And hee <hi>wiſhes that this Rite and Custom</hi> were again reſtored and practiſed in the Church of God, <hi>Talem ergò manuum impoſitionem quae ſimpliciter loco benedictionis fiat, laudo, &amp; reſtitutam hodiè in purum uſum velim;</hi> and gives weightie reaſons of what benefit it would bee to the Church. Sect. 13.</p>
               <p>Or ſecondly, by <hi>impoſition</hi> of hands muſt bee underſtood a <hi>Rite or Ceremonie</hi> uſed in the <hi>Ordination</hi> of Miniſters. Now <hi>chuſe which ſenſ you pleaſ;</hi> if the later, then you confeſs that <hi>Ordination</hi> is a <hi>Scripture-principle,</hi> to bee acknowledged of all Chriſtians, and ſo you <hi>yield our firſt queſtion;</hi> if the <hi>former ſenſ,</hi> then you acknowledg <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> to bee a <hi>Scripture principle,</hi> fit for all men to imbrace; and ſo you yield our <hi>later queſtion:</hi> But why may wee not underſtand <hi>this laying on of hands in both reſpects?</hi> and ſo conclude <hi>both points? judicent docti.</hi> It is <hi>neceſſarie for all men</hi> to bee inſtructed and catechized in <hi>theſe ſix Principles</hi> of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and to believ.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That wee muſt <hi>Repent of all our ſins,</hi> which are dead works, and turn from them to ſerv God in newneſs of life.</item>
                  <item>2. That <hi>penitent</hi> perſons muſt <hi>believ in God and reſt on his mercie</hi> in Chriſt for ſalvation.</item>
                  <item>3. And, (for the <hi>grounding of people</hi> in Religion) that they bee inſtructed concerning the <hi>nature, uſe and ſignification</hi> of Baptiſm, whereby wee are baptized and <hi>planted into Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 6.3.</note> 
                     <hi>to bee partakers</hi> of the benefits of <hi>his death.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. And farther to bee <hi>instructed, that by laying</hi> on of hands, <hi>our baptized Infants ought to bee trained</hi> up in the knowledg and fear of the Lord <hi>ſeaſoned</hi> with the principles of Chriſt's Religion; and that <hi>for their good and the inſtruction</hi> of the whole Church, and for right diſpencing of Goſpel-Ordinances, and the <hi>means of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> it is neceſſarie that <hi>a ſucceſſion of Miniſters bee Ordained,</hi> for gathering and perfecting the Saints till wee all meet in Heaven.</item>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40677:27"/>
                  <item>5. And that all Chriſtian people <hi>bee taught to believ</hi> the Reſurrection of the dead.</item>
                  <item>6. And the <hi>last judgment,</hi> whereby all men ſhall be judged, and <hi>eternally</hi> diſpoſed of,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10.</note> according to that they have don in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, whether it bee good or bad.</item>
               </list>
               <p>O Lord our God, God of all Grace, Father of all mercies, vouchſafe for thy Son's ſake, to open all our underſtandings, that wee may conceiv and bow all our hearts to imbrace all ſaving Truthes: And let us never bee of the number of thoſe that ſtrive or rebel againſt the light.</p>
               <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40677:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
